<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../css/stylesheet.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<TEI id="frp.nyt.19721105">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Indians Staying in U.S. Building"</title>
<title type="sub">Marshals Delay Eviction While Negotiations Go On</title>
<author n=""></author>
<principal></principal>
<editor></editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor:</resp>
<name>Jason A. Heppler</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2008</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher></publisher>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>Department of History</addrLine>
<addrLine>612 Oldfather Hall</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="ISBN"></idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<!-- <notesStmt>
<note></note>
</notesStmt> -->

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author n=""></author>
<title level="a" type="main">"Indians Staying in U.S. Building"</title>
<title level="a" type="sub"></title>
<title level="a" type="sub"></title>
<title level="j">New York Times</title>
<editor></editor>
<pubPlace></pubPlace>
<publisher></publisher>
<date value="1972-11-05">05November 1972</date>
<biblScope type="page">37</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

<!-- <notesStmt>
<note></note> -->
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-11-07</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Jason A. Heppler</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Initial encoding</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>200y-mm-dd</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Transcribed by Jason A. Heppler</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Original Transcription</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<pb n="p37"/>


<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Indians Staying in U.S. Building</head>
<head type="sub">Marshals Delay Eviction While Negotiations Go On</head>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source</hi>:  <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, p. 37</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="date">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Date</hi>:  November 05, 1972</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="author">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Author(s)</hi>:  N/A</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<p>Members of the American Indian Movement continued to occupy the Bureau of Indian Affairs building today after an early morning agreement with Government officials that Federal marshals would not try to evict them pending further negotiations over their grievances.</p>

<p>The occupaiton violated a court order that was issued last night by Judge John H. Pratt of the United States District Court here.</p>

<p>About 400 Indian militants had been given until last midnight to end their seizure of the building, which entered its third day.  But when they refused to leave, Judge Pratt declined to issue a contempt citation that would have authorized the marshals to move in to evict them.</p>

<p>Negotiations between the Indians and the Government were recessed tonight until tomorrow morning.</p>

<p><head type="sub">'Broken Treaties' Cited</head></p>

<p>The Indian militants had barricaded themselves in the Indian bureau building to press demands for immediate Government action to redress "crimes" against the Indian people.  They demanded revision of what they termed "broken treaties" with the Indians and reform of land policies on reservations.</p>

<p>As the midnight deadline for their eviction approached, the situation inside the building grew tense.</p>

<p>Two false reports that Federal marshals were trying to enter the building caused the Indians to gather clubs, gasoline bombs and typewriters for a confrontation with authorities.</p>

<p>As the night wore on, however, many Indians slumped in chairs, under tables and in hallways to get frequently interrupted sleep.</p>

<p><head type="sub">3 Offers From Government</head></p>

<p>Between 11:30 P.M. and 4 A.M. Government officials made three offers to provide accomodations for them outside the building.  A small group, including children and the elderly, accepted.</p>

<p>When presented with the third offer, Vernon Bellecourt, an Indian leader, said "We gave them a list of conditions earlier today and they responded by offering us accomodations."</p>

<p>"Is there anyone here who desires lodging?" he asked.</p>

<p>The Indians shouted "No" and began chanting what was described as their national anthem.</p>

<p>More than 500 Indians came to the capital this week in what they described as a "Trail of Broken Treaties" caravan to protest the plight of Indians who, they contend, are the "forgotten original Americans."</p>

<p>Besides their demands for speedy revision of their treaties with the Government and for reforms in the ownership of land and natural resources, they added to these yesterday demands for the dismissal of three top Federal officials who deal with Indian problems.</p>

<p><head type="sub">'Native Indian Embassy'</head></p>

<p>At a 4:14 A.M. news conference Mr. Bellecourt, who asked to be identified by his tribal name Waubunina, said that the building has been declared "the native Indian embassy."</p>

<p>Mr. Bellecourt also declared that the group would go ahead with a planned religious service in Arlington National Cemetery to honor Indian war dead this weekend despite a ban against it by the United States Army.  The Army's position was upheld yesterday by Judge Howard F. Corcoran of the United States District Court.</p>

<p>The Indians appealed this decision today before the United States Court of Appeals of the District of Columbia.  The appeals court heard arguments this afternoon and said that it would make a ruling tomorrow.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
