<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../css/stylesheet.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<TEI id="frp.nyt.19721104">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Indians in Capital Defy a Court Order"</title>
<title type="sub"></title>
<author n="Blair, William M.">William M. Blair</author>
<principal></principal>
<editor></editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor:</resp>
<name>Jason A. Heppler</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2008</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher></publisher>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>Department of History</addrLine>
<addrLine>612 Oldfather Hall</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="ISBN"></idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<!-- <notesStmt>
<note></note>
</notesStmt> -->

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author n="Blair, William M.">William M. Blair</author>
<title level="a" type="main">"Indians in Capital Defy a Court Order"</title>
<title level="a" type="sub"></title>
<title level="a" type="sub"></title>
<title level="j">New York Times</title>
<editor></editor>
<pubPlace></pubPlace>
<publisher></publisher>
<date value="1972-11-04">04 November 1972</date>
<biblScope type="page">42</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

<!-- <notesStmt>
<note></note> -->
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-11-07</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Jason A. Heppler</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Initial encoding</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>200y-mm-dd</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Transcribed by Jason A. Heppler</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Original Transcription</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<pb n="p42"/>


<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Indians in Capital Defy a Court Order</head>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source</hi>:  <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, p. 42</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="date">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Date</hi>:  November 04, 1972</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="author">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Author(s)</hi>:  William M. Blair</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<p>American Indian militants defied a Federal court order last night and barricaded themselves in the Bureau of Indian Affairs building for the second successive night.</p>

<p>The militants, who are demanding immediate action by the Government to redress "crimes" against the Indian people, were served with a court order banning any further occupation of the building.</p>

<p>The order, signed by Judge John H. Pratt of the United States District Court, was served by Federal marshals.</p>

<p>After a midnight deadline to leave the building expired, an assistant Federal marshal, James F. Palmer, offered the defiant Indians food and shelter if they vacated the building.  The offer was rejected early this morning.</p>

<p>The truce reached late Thursday night after the protesters had seized control of the building, collapsed yesterday morning as the Indians made additional demands that the Government speed efforts to improve conditions for Indians.</p>

<p>These demands included speedy revision of treaties with Indians, reform of land policies that the Indians contend are squeezing their economic livelihood, and the dismissal of at least three Federal officials who deal with Indian problems.</p>

<p>The White House Thursday night overruled Department of the Interior officials who had recommended police action to dislodge the nearly 500 protesters, permitted the Indians to hold the bureau's building.  They barricaded themselves in the six-story structure at 19th Street and Constitution Avenue, Northwest, and caused damage estimated at $250,000.  They took over most offices on the first three floors.</p>

<p>Early last evening the Indians again barricaded the doors of the bureau building.  Louis R. Bruce, the Indian affairs commissioner, and a few other bureau officials, stayed with them.  There was no estimate of the number within the building, which the Indians had kept open during the day.</p>

<p><head type="sub">Campaign Trip Canceled</head></p>

<p>Secretary of the Interior Rogers C. B. Morton, whose department includes the Indian agency, broke off a campaign trip to fly back to Washington for negotiations with the Indians.  Commissioner Bruce, who is an Indian, headed a round of continuous talks, saying that the young activist Indians had his support.</p>

<p>"I'm willing to stick it out to assist you," Mr. Bruce told the Indian leaders, who contend that they represent a coalition of 250 of the country's 300 tribes.</p>

<p>A spokesman for the Interior Department contended that the group as made up largely of urban Indians and was "unrepresentative" of the country's 850,000 Indians.  He said that no tribal chiefs with whom the bureau usually deals were present and only a sprinkling of tribal council members had joined the protesters.</p>

<p><head type="sub">'Forgotten Americans'</head></p>

<p>The Indians traveled here in what they termed a "Trail of Broken Treaties" caravan to focus attention on the plight of Indians who they contend are the "forgotten original Americans."</p>

<p>They seek a complete overhaul of the Bureau of Indian Affairs, the agency entrusted with responsibility for Indians.  It has been the target of Indian discontent for many years, but in recent years activist Indians have stepped up efforts to protect their lands and mineral and water rights, and have pressed for new programs to better Indian eduation opportunities both in and outside reservations.</p>

<p>Their demands include the dismissal of John O. Crow, the deputy Indian commissioner, whom they charge was named to "hold the lid on changes" despite President Nixon's assurances that he wanted the bureau "shaken up" to meet Indian problems.</p>

<p>They also demanded yesterday the dismissals of Harrison E. Loesch, the Assistant Secretary of the Interior for land management, who supervises the Indian Bureau, and Robert Robertson, executive director of the Office of Indian Opportunitiy under vice President Agnew.</p>

<p>Mr. Loesch and Mr. Robertson headed the negotiations that led to the temporary truce Thursday night.  That agreement provided that the Indians leave the Bureau of Indian Affairs buildiung and move to a Government auditorium several blocks down Constitution Avenue.  The Indians, however, refused to leave the bureau's building today when they were told they would not be allowed in the auditorium until they had cleared the Indian Bureau.</p>

<p>The agreement also provided that Bradford Patterson, a White House assistant, would give written replies to the Indians' demands for Executive and Congressional action on "broken treaties" and related problems.</p>

<p><head type="sub">'Meaningful Change'</head></p>

<p>The Indians renamed the Indian affairs building "the Native American Sovereign Embassy."</p>

<p>"We are trying to bring about some meaningful change for the Indian community," said Dennis Banks, national field director of the American Indian Movement, an activist organization whose members have staged demonstrations throughout the country.</p>

<p>Mr. Banks charged that the Government honored treaties with foreign countries but had emasculated treaties that were signed 100 or more years ago with native Americans.</p>

<p>The Indians went to a Federal court yesterday for an injunction against the United States Army's ban on a march they planned to Arlington National Cemetery for "spiritual services" to honor Indians slain in wars.  The Army had ruled that the Indian Caravan was a "partisan" event under present regulations.</p>

<p>Indian leaders canceled a march to Arlington yesterday afternoon when the Army's position was upheld by Judge Howard F. Corcoran of the United States District Court here.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
