<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../css/stylesheet.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<TEI id="frp.ct.19721105">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">"Judge Stalls Eviction of Indians; U.S., Protesters Hold Site Talks"</title>
<title type="sub"></title>
<author n=""></author>
<principal></principal>
<editor></editor>
<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor:</resp>
<name>Jason A. Heppler</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2008</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher></publisher>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>Department of History</addrLine>
<addrLine>612 Oldfather Hall</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="ISBN"></idno>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<!-- <notesStmt>
<note></note>
</notesStmt> -->

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author n=""></author>
<title level="a" type="main">"Judge Stalls Eviction of Indians; U.S., Protesters Hold Site Talks"</title>
<title level="a" type="sub"></title>
<title level="a" type="sub"></title>
<title level="j">Chicago Tribune</title>
<editor></editor>
<pubPlace></pubPlace>
<publisher></publisher>
<date value="1972-12-03">05 November 1972</date>
<biblScope type="page">B10</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>

<!-- <notesStmt>
<note></note> -->
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2008-11-07</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Jason A. Heppler</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Initial encoding</item>
</change>
<change>
<date>200y-mm-dd</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Transcribed by Jason A. Heppler</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Original Transcription</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<pb n="pB10"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Chicago Tribune</hi>, November 05, 1972, p. B10.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Judge Stalls Eviction of Indians; U.S., Protesters Hold Site Talks</head>

<p>Hundreds of American Indians, some wearing warpaint and armed with makeshift tomahawks, held the Bureau of Indian Affairs for a third night today when a federal judge refused to allow the government to evict them.</p>

<p>Judge John Pratt, of the United States district court, refused to sign a show cause order or a contempt citation late today, delaying until at least tomorrow any action against the Indians.  They had said they were "prepared to die" in defense of the building they have occupied since Thursday.</p>

<p>Pratt ordered the Indians to leave the building last night but when they refused he ordered the government to try to negotiate a peaceful end to the protest.  A team of negotiators from the Interior, Justice and GSA offices met with 10 Indian representatives tonight but both sides said no progress had been made and the talks were recessed until tomorrow morning.</p>

<p>However, Indian spokesmen said they were encouraged by government offers of free space at area airports.  They rejected the offers but said the situation "looks very positive because of the fact the negotiators realize our commitment here--that we are willing to die," said Russell Means, a spokesman for the "Trail of Broken Treaties," a coalition of 200 Indian tribes that came to Washington to help their people.</p>

<p>Interior Department officials said Indian representatives looked over alternate quarters offered by the government at another federal building and two nearby military installations, but decided to stay where they were.</p>	

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="pA8"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Chicago Tribune</hi>, November 06, 1972, p. A8.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Indians Occupying U.S. Building Ask Nixon to Intercede</head>

<p>Indians occupying the Bureau of Indian Affairs building urged President Nixon tonight to help find a solution in the impasse between the demonstrators and federal officials, who have given the Indians an ultimatum to evacuate by tomorrow morning.</p>

<p>Dennis Banks, field director for the American Indian Movement, said the Indians were rejecting the latest overture from the government, an offer of an interdepartmental auditorium--the same facility proffered repeatedly in the last four days--with the addition of shower facilities.</p>

<p><head type="sub">350 in Building</head></p>

<p>Banks said if the Indians had agreed to move into the auditorium, federal officials would have arranged for them an appointment with Interior Secretary Rogers C. B. Morton.</p>

<p>An estimated 200 Indians took over the BIA building last Thursday as part of a protest against "life in a white-dominated America."  The number inside the building today was put at about 350.</p>

<p>Banks said no new negotiations are planned, and that appointments the Indians said had been arranged with top White House assistant John Ehrlichman and Leonard Garment, his minority-affairs consultant, have been canceled.  He said the Indians did not know the reason, but an Interior Department spokesman said the appointments were never arranged.</p>

<p>"Both this administration and our caravan are backed up against the election," Banks said.  "Zero hour is too close to provide meaningful discussion.</p>

<p><head type="sub">Meet in Teepee</head></p>

<p>"The government wants this building, they don't care about us."</p>

<p>The Indians' policy council met for 45 minutes tonight within the teepee set up on the BIA lawn to mull over the latest offer from the federal negotiators.</p>

<p>During that time, they refined the wording of the telegram they were sending to Nixon.  It asks him to appoint a special 12-member committee to oversee the situation, including five government representatives and seven Indians.</p>

<p>It also asks that a meeting of the commission be convened by Nixon by no later than 8 a.m. tomorrow--the newest deadline for evacuation of the building.  Nixon is at the Western White House in San Clemente, Cal.</p>

<p><head type="sub">Ultimatum Is Given</head></p>

<p>A government spokesman said after offering the latest proposal that if the Indians rejected it, a federal judge would be asked to sign a contempt order giving marshals authority to eject the demonstrators from the building.</p>

<p>Vernon Bellecourt, national coordinator of the American Indian Movement, told newsman earlier tonight that Erlichman and Garment had agreed to meet with the Indians.  The government said no such meeting had been arranged.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>



<text>
<body>

<pb n="pA1"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Chicago Tribune</hi>, November 10, 1972, p. A8.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Indians Ripped Up Federal Building</head>
<head type="sub">Indian Vandalism to Federal Building Is Set at $530,000</head>

	<p>Protesting Indians caused $530,000 damage to the office of the Bureau of Indian Affairs, government officials said today.  They estimated that employees will not be able to return to work until at least a week from tomorrow.</p>
				
	<p>Inspecting the debris-strewn four-story building, investigators found hundreds of thousands of letters and other official documents several inches deep.</p>
				
	<p>The General Services Administration said structural damage of $250,000 includes the cost of repairing holes in the walls, smashed windows, ruined plumbing, and removing grafitti on the walls.</p>
				
	<p><head type="sub">Files Not Counted</head></p>
	
	<p>Another $280,000 was estimated to be lost in typewriters, rugs, office furniture and other equipment.  Not included was the cost of damaged files and broken Indian paintings, pottery, baskets and sculptures.</p>
				
	<p>The Indian demonstrators, numbering about 400 at one time, took hundreds of documents with them as they left yesterday, but Interior Department spokesmen said they still don't know which documents they are.</p>

	<p>Departing before a court ordered deadline, some of the Indians had said the documents contained "highly incriminating evidence" against Western congressmen.</p>
	
	<p><head type="sub">Employees in Building</head></p>
				
	<p>The BIA said a handful of employs were in the building today to retrieve property "but most won't be back until Nov. 17 at the earliest."</p>
				
	<p>One effect, a BIA spokesman said, will be that many advisory and policy functions will be suspended, perhaps delaying decisions on many Indian matters.</p>
				
	<p>However, the 200 BIA schools will not be affected because their headquarters are in Albuquerque, he said.</p>
				
	<p>The departing Indians also left behind a roomful of Molotov cocktails and fire extinguishers filled with gasoline.  Indians repeatedly warned newsmen not to smoke on the second floor during the last few days of the occupation because of the gasoline that had been spread along the halls.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>



<text>
<body>

<pb n="p3"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi>  Michael Satchell,<hi rend="italic"> Chicago Tribune</hi>, November 13, 1972, p. 3.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Led Building Takeover: Criminal Record of 3 Indian Leaders Told</head>

<p>Three of the principal leaders of Indians who looted files, destroyed or stole irreplaceable Indian artifacts, and caused nearly $2 million in damage during last week's six-day occupation of the Bureau of Indian Affairs building here have extensive criminal records in Minneapolis.</p>

<p>A high police official there said that Dennis Banks, Clyde Bellecourt, and his brother Vernon Bellecourt, had served sentences in Minnesota penitentaries for a veriety of felony offenses including burglary, aggravated assault, and armed robbery.</p>

<p><head type="sub">3 Lead Indian Group</head></p>

<p>All three men are leaders of the American Indian Movement.  Banks, one of the cofounders of AIM, is the national field director and lives in Minneapolis.  Vernon Bellecourt is a national codirector of the organization and runs the Denver chapter.  Clyde Bellecourt is executive director of the Minneapolis group, one of the biggest with more than 100 members.</p>

<p>AIM also has $113,000 federal grant to operate educational facilities for Indians.</p>

<p>The Federal Bureua of Investigation is conducting a "full-scale" investigation into the destruction and theft at the Bureau of Indian Affairs building, and Justice Department sources said, "we will prosecute in any area we can."</p>

<p><head type="sub">4 Leaders Noted</head></p>

<p>The two Bellecourts, Banks, and a fourth Indian, Russell Means of Porcupine, S. D., emerged as the leaders of the group holding the building.</p>

<p>Means was formerly an AIM national director, but resigned and returned to the Oglalla Sioux Pine Ridge Reservation in South Dakota.</p>

<p>During the siege, Vernon Bellecourt and Means were the most visible leaders, serving as spokesman for the protesters and handling inquiries from the news media.  Inside the building, Banks and Clyde Bellecourt were involved in security and other internal aspects of the occupation.</p>

<p>The AIM leaders took over the Trail of Broken Treaties campaign, a peaceful lobbying effort organized principally by Robert Burnett, a Rosebud, S. D., Sioux.  Burnett gradually lost control of the program and has since condemned the AIM leaders for their theft of Indian documents and destruction of art.</p>

<p><head type="sub">Police Records Told</head></p>

<p>A Minneapolis police official said Banks had been convicted 15 times on charges including assault and battery and burglary.</p>

<p>Clyde Bellecourt, the official said, was found guilty of armed robbery in 1954 and was sentenced to serve 2 to 15 years in prison.  After parole police said, he was convicted in 1958 of burglary, sentenced to 5 years in prison, paroled again and then was convicted of burglary in 1960 and paroled in 1964.</p>

<p>Police said Clyde Belleoucrt now is facing charges on aggrevated criminal property damage involving vandalism at a Minneapolis restaurant.</p>

<p>Vernon Bellecourt was convicted of burglary in 1950 and armed robbery in 1953, receiving a prison sentence of 5 to 40 years.</p>

<p><head type="sub">Formulated in Jail</head></p>

<p>The organization, according to one national Indian activst, "was cooked up in the Minnesota penitentiary."  AIM is described by other leaders as "militant" and "action oriented."  It has 4,500 members in the U.S. and Canada.</p>

<p>A spokesman for the Office of Economic Opportunity confirmed last week that AIM received the $113,000 grant on May 1 to fund schools in Milawukee, Minneapolis, and St. Paul.  The schools were described on grant applications as institutions for rehabilitating dropouts.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>



<text>
<body>

<pb n="p7"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Chicago Tribune</hi>, December 03, 1972, p. 7.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Three Aides Fired at Indian Bureau</head>

<p>Interior Secretary Rogers C. B. Morton today stripped supervision of Indian affairs from the top three men involved, saying he was taking personal command to "put Indian operations back to work."</p>

<p>Morton acted as name-calling and squabbling increased and finally surfaced this week among Bureau of Indian Affairs executives, in the wake of the six-day occupation of the BIAs Washington headquarters by hundreds of Indian demonstrators.</p>

<p>In a statement, Morton said he was removing all present authority for Indian affairs from Assistant Secretary of the Interior Harrison Loesch, BIA Commissioner Louis R. Bruce and Deputy BIA Commissioner John O. Crow.</p>

<p><head type="sub">Bodman Takes Charge</head></p>

<p>He named Richard S. Bodman, assistant secretary for management and budget, to take charge of the BIA.</p>

<p>"I have taken this action because I believe it is essential to the well-being of the American Indian that we return our Indian programs to operational effectiveness without delay," Morton said.</p>

<p>On Thursday, Crow first publicly criticized his boss, Bruce, and said one of them had to go.  He said "I didn't like the support he gave to the unruly mob . . . He couldn't administer anything."</p>

<p>Crow said he had the tacit support of Loesch, who has had overall resposibility for the BIA and who named Crow to his position next to Bruce despite protests of some Indians that the purpose was to thwart Bruce's reform of the BIA.</p>

<p>Loesch and Crow were the targets of the ire of the Trail of Broken Treaties caravan demonstrators in early November, who asked that both be fired for being allegedly "anti-Indian."</p>

<p><head type="sub">Stays With Demonstrators</head></p>

<p>Bruce had not aligned himself with the demonstrators but he said he agreed with many of their goals and, to dramatize this, he stayed with them in the BIA building for 24 hours after they barricaded themselves in.</p>

<p>This ended the second day when Loesch ordered Bruce to leave.</p>

<p>The first of a series of congressional investigations of the BIA building takeover begins Monday before Rep. James A. Haley (D., Fla.), chairman of the House Indian affairs subcommittee.  An Interior spokesman said Bruce, Crow, and Loesch will appear to testify as scheduled.</p>

<p>A White House spokesman had said earlier today that he'd never seen any federal agency as polarized as the Interior and BIA.</p>

<p>"They can't serve the people they are meant to serve," he said.</p>
	

</div1>
</body>
</text>




<text>
<body>

<pb n="pB10"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Chicago Tribune</hi>, December 05, 1972, p. B10.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Politics Admitted in Indian Deal</head>

	<p>Rogers C. B. Morton today said "the political environment" was considered when the administration decided against forcing protesting Indians out of the Bureau of Indian Affairs shortly before electon day last month.</p>

	<p>Morton told a House Interior subcommittee hearing, however, that there was no White House "takeover" of negotiations which saw the government pay the Indians some $65,000 in expenses to leave the building they occupied for seven days and to which they caused an estimated $1 million in damage.</p>

	<p>The panel summoned Interior officials to explain who made decisions in dealing with the Indians, who were represented by the Trail of Broken Treaties organization in their claims that the government broke promises made to Indians in administration of reservations.</p>

	<p>The protesters, numbering about 500, barricaded themselves in the building on NOv. 2 and vowed to fight to the death against any police action to force them out.  They left voluntarily on NOv. 8 after negotiating an agreement with White House officials led by John Ehrlichman, President Nixon's top domestic affairs adviser.</p>

	<p>Morton told newsmen after the morning hearing ended that "no political decisions were made" in dealing with the Indians, but he added that "the political environment was fully evaluated and the decision was made to go the court route" instead of taking police action.</p>
	
</div1>
</body>
</text>



<text>
<body>

<pb n="p"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  .......</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Minneapolis Tribune</hi>, November 4, 1972, p. #.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Protesting Indians refuse to leave BIA building despite court order</head>

	<p>Militant American Indian leaders, refusing to obey a court order to vacate Bureau of Indian Affairs (BIA) headquarters, armed themselves with makeshift weapons Friday night and vowed not to leave without a fight.</p>

	<p>Given an hour's grace period to comply with the order, the several hundred Indian protesters occupying the building near the White House instead used the time to clear the quarters of women and children and set up barricades.</p>

	<p>One leader, Dennis Banks of the American Indian Movement, exhorted what he called his "swiftest and strongest braves" to "do anything you have to do" to evade being taken away.</p>

	<p>The occupying force used broken-up furniture, electrical cable and any object at hand to barricade stairways and corridors in preparation to repulse the <sic>seige</sic> they expected. Many were armed with small missiles and sharp objects.  At various times reporters spotted a gun or two.  Federal authorities acting under Interior Department direction massed a strike force of U.S. marshals, metropolitan police, U.S. park police and officers of the Government Services Administration guard service.</p>

	<p>Indian Commissioner Louis Bruce said he would stay in his office but added that he would not participate should any fighting take place between Indians and marshals.</p>

	<p>"<sic>i've</sic> [sic] been trying to stop this," Bruce said. "I was concerned about housing for all the people and I was hoping the group might decide to leave peacefully and maybe this might have brought about more services (for the Indians here)."</p>

	<p>Earlier in the evening intensive efforts to negotiate a way out of the incipient confrontation apparently broke down. They included a conference at the White House with administration officials by lawyer Terrence Sidley, the attorney for the Native American Legal Defense and Educational Fund.</p>

	<p>The immediate issue was whether the Indian group would leave the BIA building, which they had occupied for more than 24 hours, and accept alternate quarters the federal government said it would provide. While leaders at first agreed to go, they apparently became suspicious of the government's intentions and changed their minds.</p>

	<p>The protest grew militant Thursday when the group, seeking to dramatize their demands for an overhaul of federal programs affecting their people, took over the five-story building and evicted its government worker occupants.</p>

	<p>The Indians gathered In Washington for the Trail of Broken Treaties Caravan to dramatize what they called their fight for survival in white America.</p>

	<p>One BIA official estimated there were about 400 protesters in the BIA building and outside on the lawn at noon yesterday.  Officials said the demonstrators had caused about $250,000 damage to the building.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>



<text>
<body>

<pb n="p"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  .......</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Minneapolis Tribune</hi>, November 7, 1972, p. #.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Indians agree to leave BIA building today, officials say</head>

	<p>Protesting Indians agreed Tuesday night to leave the Bureau of Indian Affairs Building they held for almost a week after reaching an agreement with government negotiators, the White House said.</p>

	<p>The provisions of the agreement were not immediately available, but Chert Phillips of the White House  press  office  said:</p>

	<p>"An agreement was reached and the Indians should be leaving Wednesday morning."</p>

	<p>The meeting with the Indians had started at around noon yesterday and went on into the evening hours, the White House spokesman said.</p>

	<p>But Vernon Bellecourt, spokesman for the American Indian Movement, said that despite the agreement, the building would not be vacated until the government acts on the issues that brought the Indians to Washington.</p>

	<p>These Include demands that treaties be respected, that the BIA be abolished and -- in apparent contradiction -- that $30 million be restored to the BIA budget.</p>

	<p>"We're supposed to be negotiating an agreement for our departure," from the Bureau of Indian Affairs Building, said Hank Adams, an Indian lawyer, moments before the talks began.</p>

	<p>But Adams cautioned that longstanding Indian grievances, as well as "provisions for allowing our people to return to our communities," also would be brought up by the Indians.</p>

	<p>The meeting was called after a U.S. District Court ordered the federal government to oust the protesters. The ouster was delayed until 9 p.m. today by the U.S. Circuit Court here.</p>

	<p>The Indians seized control of the building Thursday after coming to Washington to protest government policies. The Indians, coming from all parts of the country, described their journey as the Trail of Broken Treaties.</p>

	<p>They strengthened security around the building following the federal court eviction order. Windows were taped, presumably to prevent shards of glass from flying about if the windows were broken, and doors were barricaded.</p>

	<p>Unconfirmed rumors also have circulated that the protesters have planted explosives or gasoline in the building and plan to destroy it if they are forcibly evicted.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>



<text>
<body>

<pb n="p95"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi>  <hi rend="italic">  New York Times</hi>, October 05, 1972, p. 95.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Indians to Drive to Capital</head>

<p>Indian leaders disclosed today plans for a series of automobile caravans to the nation's capital to "remind elected officials of the common mistreatment and neglect of the American Indian."  Vernon Bellecourt, national codirector of the American Indian Movement, said that seven separate caravans would start this month from Seattle, San Francisco, Los Angeles and several Canadian cities, hoping to reach Washington on Nov. 1.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="p31"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>   The <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> reports that groups of American Indian activists are converging on Washington D.C. for peaceful demonstrations.  Activists claim that up to 10,000 activists will arrive at the demonstration on the eve of the 1972 election.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi>  <hi rend="italic">  New York Times</hi>, October 31, 1972, p. 31.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Indians to Begin Capital Protests</head>
<head type="sub">Demonstrations This Week to Ask Wide U.S. Help</head>

<p>Groups of American Indians will be in the nation's capital this week in an effort to gain through "peaceful demonstrations" the economic and social benefits that they believe are due them as "first citizens of the land."</p>

<p>This is the stated purpose of "Trail of Broken Treaties Caravan," a bus and auto trip across the country on the eve of the Presidential election to impress upon elected officials the need for solving Indian problems.</p>

<p>"We come here in peace," Robert Burnette, a Rosebud Sioux, told a news conference today.  "We want to remain in peace."</p>

<p>Mr. Burnette, who is former chairman of the Rosebud Sioux tribe, added:</p>

<p>"We are putting Americans on notice that something must be done, or we may have to take things in our own hands."</p>

<p>He estimated that up to 10,000 Indians and "friends" would gather here for the week-long demonstration.  They will set up a "symbolic camp" in West Potomac Park, the scene of demonstrations by other minority groups in the past.</p>

<p>The Indians, he said, "deliberately chose" election time to voice their demands, not particularly as a demonstration against the Nixon Administration, but to present an agenda for action on Indian problems by next Congress and the next Administration.  These problems range from education to physical improvement on reservations and aid to INdians living in urban areas, he said.</p>

<p>Mr. Burnette said about 80 Indian organizations were involved, although he conceded that the groups were divided by differences in approach to Indian problems.  Nevertheless, he said, they are united in believing that economic and other pressures were destroying the Indian culture.</p>

<p>The caravans are an extension of the demonstrations by young activst Indians against the Bureau of Indian Affairs, an agency of the Department of the Interior.</p>

<p>They accuse the bureau of failing to recognize the Indians' rights to their "home lands" and the right to administer their own affairs.  They say the white man's economy threatens to rob them of their natural resources, from underground minerals to timber.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>



<text>
<body>

<pb n="p81"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  The initial <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> report of the Bureau of Indian Affairs occupation reports on the capture of the federal building by 500 activists.  The newspaper reports that the Nixon administration allows the activists to continue holding the building until the next day.  Negotiations begin between the occupiers and Bureau of Indian Affairs officials.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  New York Times</hi>, November 3, 1972, p. 81.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">500 Indians Seize U.S. Building After Scuffle With Capital Police</head>

	<p>About 500 American Indians protesting injustices, took control tonight of the Bureau of Indian Affairs building after scuffles with the police outside and inside the building.</p>

	<p>Late tonight, Nixon Administration officials were apparently prepared to let the Indians bivouac in the building until morning.  Negotiations between Indian leaders and Administration officials continued without resolution.</p>

	<p>Women and about two dozen children were bedded on the third floor of the building, which the Indians scaled off.  Many of the demonstrators had brought bedrolls and sleeping bags.</p>

	<p>A force of about 150 policemen surrounded the building at the closing hour, but Department of the Interior officials held the policemen back as young activist Indians barricaded themselves inside the building by piling furniture against doors.</p>

	<p>No arrests were made.  Meanwhile, leaders of the "Trail of Broken Treaties," a caravan of Indians bent on emphasizing the rights of Indians as the first Americans, sought to arrange meetings with Administration officials to solve the impasse over their demands for housing and food during their march on Washington.</p>

	<p>The sole major Indian bureau official within the building appeared to be John O. Crow, associate commissioner of Indian affairs.</p>

	<p>Mr. Crow said that after the first scuffles outside the building, the situation was "calm" as the 500 Indian protesters awaited word on whether they would gain a place to sleep and quarters from which to conduct further negotiations.</p>

	<p><head type="sub">Furniture Broken</head></p>

	<p>During the melee, windows were broken and furniture was ripped apart to provide the militant Indians with clubs.  Carl Shaw, an information officer, said that some duplicating machines were overturned and papers from officers of the information section were scattered through the halls.</p>

	<p>Mr. Shaw said that he and others from the information office were forced to elave the building through a window on the basement level.  He said that all calls to his office were taken over by the protesters.</p>

	<p>Louis R. Bruce, the Indian Affairs Commissioner, said that he and other officials had decided that the protesters would be permitted to stay in the building tonight and expressed hope that all problems could beresolved tomorrow.</p>

	<p>"We can work with them," said Mr. Bruce, a Mohawk and Ogalla Sioux from New York, after meeting late tonight with the leaders of the militants.</p>

	<p>The protesters were led by members of the American Indian Movement, a militant group that has been in the forefront of Indian groups demanding more aid from the Nixon Administration for Indian economic and social needs.</p>

	<p>Leaders of the protest met tonight with various officials including Bradford Patterson, a White House assistant for minority affairs.  Mr. Patterson earlier had made public letters to the Indian leaders, telling them that President Nixon was unable to meet with them but that the Administration would assist them in establishing a "meaningful dialogue."</p>

	<p>Newsmen seeking entrance to the building late tonight were turned away by the police.  Some newsmen within the building were told that they could not leave.</p>

	<p>Telephone calls to various offices were answered by Indians who identified themsleves as part of the invading group.</p>

	<p>The Bureau of Indian Affairs said that its offices would be closed tomorrow while the negotiations continued.</p>

	<p>"Answering the 'phone and telling you that the Pigs are all around us," was the response.</p>

	<p>Earlier, Mrs. Martha Gras, a 71-year-old Pawnee Indian, appeared to sum up the sentiment of the Indian gathering.</p>

	<p>"There are nothing but crooks and liars up here," she shouted at cheering Indians in an auditorium in the building.  "They'll steal you blind."</p>

	<p>Martha, as she appeared to be widely known to "The Trail of Broken Treaties" caravan, drew cries of "Right on" as she sought to detail injustices the Indians had suffered from white men.</p>

	<p>More than 500 Indians came to the nation's capital for a week-long protest against broken treaties and failure of the Government to carry out trust responsibilities to the original Americas.  They abandoned a program laid out by their leaders and gathered in the auditorium of the Bureau of Indian Affairs at the Department of the Interior.</p>

	<p>The scheduled program broke down because of a lack of housing, food and funds that the Indians, mainly young activists, had expected to find there.  They protested that the Government had failed to assist them and that the first caravan contingent, which arrived here last night, had to spend the night in a "rat-infested" church that had served minority groups in past demonstrations.</p>

	<p><head type="sub">'Listening for 300 Years'</head></p>

	<p>They vowed to stay in the Indian Affairs Bureau until the Government provided adequate facilities.  Harrison E. Loesch, Assistant Secretary of the Interior, and other Administration officials promised to "explore" every possible avenue to give them housing and other facilities for their stay.</p>

	<p>Mr. Loesch sought to assure the Indians that the Nixon Administration was dedicated to meeting their economic and social needs.  He cited budget increases and other measures designed to aid Indians in education and in water and fishing rights as evidence of the Administration's good will.</p>

	<p>The Indians shouted back at him, "Harrison, you don't know anything about Indian affairs."  Others demanded: "You should turn the bureau over to us; we should be over you." and "We've been listening to you for 300 years."</p>

	<p>Nearly forgotten in the heated, confused meeting with Mr. Loesch and other Government officials was a 20-point program drawn up by a group of Indians who had started from the West Coast and who visited various Western reservations for workshops on the way to Washington.</p>

	<p>The Indians' proposals called for the Government to make mandatory the judicial enforcement of their existing treaty rights, for restoration of lands taken from Indians in earlier years, and for elimination of "inequities" in ownership or control of national resources by which, the Indians contend, white men control their lands.</p>

	<p>The Indians had arrived here on buses, station wagons and other vehicles, packed with sleeping gear and other necessities.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>




<text>
<body>

<pb n="p42"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi>  William M. Blair,<hi rend="italic"> New York Times</hi>, November 04, 1972, p. 42.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Indians in Capital Defy a Court Order</head>

<p>American Indian militants defied a Federal court order last night and barricaded themselves in the Bureau of Indian Affairs building for the second successive night.</p>

<p>The militants, who are demanding immediate action by the Government to redress "crimes" against the Indian people, were served with a court order banning any further occupation of the building.</p>

<p>The order, signed by Judge John H. Pratt of the United States District Court, was served by Federal marshals.</p>

<p>After a midnight deadline to leave the building expired, an assistant Federal marshal, James F. Palmer, offered the defiant Indians food and shelter if they vacated the building.  The offer was rejected early this morning.</p>

<p>The truce reached late Thursday night after the protesters had seized control of the building, collapsed yesterday morning as the Indians made additional demands that the Government speed efforts to improve conditions for Indians.</p>

<p>These demands included speedy revision of treaties with Indians, reform of land policies that the Indians contend are squeezing their economic livelihood, and the dismissal of at least three Federal officials who deal with Indian problems.</p>

<p>The White House Thursday night overruled Department of the Interior officials who had recommended police action to dislodge the nearly 500 protesters, permitted the Indians to hold the bureau's building.  They barricaded themselves in the six-story structure at 19th Street and Constitution Avenue, Northwest, and caused damage estimated at $250,000.  They took over most offices on the first three floors.</p>

<p>Early last evening the Indians again barricaded the doors of the bureau building.  Louis R. Bruce, the Indian affairs commissioner, and a few other bureau officials, stayed with them.  There was no estimate of the number within the building, which the Indians had kept open during the day.</p>

<p><head type="sub">Campaign Trip Canceled</head></p>

<p>Secretary of the Interior Rogers C. B. Morton, whose department includes the Indian agency, broke off a campaign trip to fly back to Washington for negotiations with the Indians.  Commissioner Bruce, who is an Indian, headed a round of continuous talks, saying that the young activist Indians had his support.</p>

<p>"I'm willing to stick it out to assist you," Mr. Bruce told the Indian leaders, who contend that they represent a coalition of 250 of the country's 300 tribes.</p>

<p>A spokesman for the Interior Department contended that the group as made up largely of urban Indians and was "unrepresentative" of the country's 850,000 Indians.  He said that no tribal chiefs with whom the bureau usually deals were present and only a sprinkling of tribal council members had joined the protesters.</p>

<p><head type="sub">'Forgotten Americans'</head></p>

<p>The Indians traveled here in what they termed a "Trail of Broken Treaties" caravan to focus attention on the plight of Indians who they contend are the "forgotten original Americans."</p>

<p>They seek a complete overhaul of the Bureau of Indian Affairs, the agency entrusted with responsibility for Indians.  It has been the target of Indian discontent for many years, but in recent years activist Indians have stepped up efforts to protect their lands and mineral and water rights, and have pressed for new programs to better Indian eduation opportunities both in and outside reservations.</p>

<p>Their demands include the dismissal of John O. Crow, the deputy Indian commissioner, whom they charge was named to "hold the lid on changes" despite President Nixon's assurances that he wanted the bureau "shaken up" to meet Indian problems.</p>

<p>They also demanded yesterday the dismissals of Harrison E. Loesch, the Assistant Secretary of the Interior for land management, who supervises the Indian Bureau, and Robert Robertson, executive director of the Office of Indian Opportunitiy under vice President Agnew.</p>

<p>Mr. Loesch and Mr. Robertson headed the negotiations that led to the temporary truce Thursday night.  That agreement provided that the Indians leave the Bureau of Indian Affairs buildiung and move to a Government auditorium several blocks down Constitution Avenue.  The Indians, however, refused to leave the bureau's building today when they were told they would not be allowed in the auditorium until they had cleared the Indian Bureau.</p>

<p>The agreement also provided that Bradford Patterson, a White House assistant, would give written replies to the Indians' demands for Executive and Congressional action on "broken treaties" and related problems.</p>

<p><head type="sub">'Meaningful Change'</head></p>

<p>The Indians renamed the Indian affairs building "the Native American Sovereign Embassy."</p>

<p>"We are trying to bring about some meaningful change for the Indian community," said Dennis Banks, national field director of the American Indian Movement, an activist organization whose members have staged demonstrations throughout the country.</p>

<p>Mr. Banks charged that the Government honored treaties with foreign countries but had emasculated treaties that were signed 100 or more years ago with native Americans.</p>

<p>The Indians went to a Federal court yesterday for an injunction against the United States Army's ban on a march they planned to Arlington National Cemetery for "spiritual services" to honor Indians slain in wars.  The Army had ruled that the Indian Caravan was a "partisan" event under present regulations.</p>

<p>Indian leaders canceled a march to Arlington yesterday afternoon when the Army's position was upheld by Judge Howard F. Corcoran of the United States District Court here.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="p37"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  The <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> first mentions the American Indian Movement (AIM) specifically as the main proponent behind the occupation of the Bureau of Indian Affairs.  The New York Times reports the activists violated Judge John H. Pratt's court order to leave the building for face penalties.  Negoiations between the activists, which the paper estimates numbers 400, and government officials continue for the third day.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi>  <hi rend="italic">  New York Times</hi>, November 05, 1972, p. 37.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Indians Staying in U.S. Building</head>
<head type="sub">Marshals Delay Eviction While Negotiations Go On</head>

<p>Members of the American Indian Movement continued to occupy the Bureau of Indian Affairs building today after an early morning agreement with Government officials that Federal marshals would not try to evict them pending further negotiations over their grievances.</p>

<p>The occupaiton violated a court order that was issued last night by Judge John H. Pratt of the United States District Court here.</p>

<p>About 400 Indian militants had been given until last midnight to end their seizure of the building, which entered its third day.  But when they refused to leave, Judge Pratt declined to issue a contempt citation that would have authorized the marshals to move in to evict them.</p>

<p>Negotiations between the Indians and the Government were recessed tonight until tomorrow morning.</p>

<p><head type="sub">'Broken Treaties' Cited</head></p>

<p>The Indian militants had barricaded themselves in the Indian bureau building to press demands for immediate Government action to redress "crimes" against the Indian people.  They demanded revision of what they termed "broken treaties" with the Indians and reform of land policies on reservations.</p>

<p>As the midnight deadline for their eviction approached, the situation inside the building grew tense.</p>

<p>Two false reports that Federal marshals were trying to enter the building caused the Indians to gather clubs, gasoline bombs and typewriters for a confrontation with authorities.</p>

<p>As the night wore on, however, many Indians slumped in chairs, under tables and in hallways to get frequently interrupted sleep.</p>

<p><head type="sub">3 Offers From Government</head></p>

<p>Between 11:30 P.M. and 4 A.M. Government officials made three offers to provide accomodations for them outside the building.  A small group, including children and the elderly, accepted.</p>

<p>When presented with the third offer, Vernon Bellecourt, an Indian leader, said "We gave them a list of conditions earlier today and they responded by offering us accomodations."</p>

<p>"Is there anyone here who desires lodging?" he asked.</p>

<p>The Indians shouted "No" and began chanting what was described as their national anthem.</p>

<p>More than 500 Indians came to the capital this week in what they described as a "Trail of Broken Treaties" caravan to protest the plight of Indians who, they contend, are the "forgotten original Americans."</p>

<p>Besides their demands for speedy revision of their treaties with the Government and for reforms in the ownership of land and natural resources, they added to these yesterday demands for the dismissal of three top Federal officials who deal with Indian problems.</p>

<p><head type="sub">'Native Indian Embassy'</head></p>

<p>At a 4:14 A.M. news conference Mr. Bellecourt, who asked to be identified by his tribal name Waubunina, said that the building has been declared "the native Indian embassy."</p>

<p>Mr. Bellecourt also declared that the group would go ahead with a planned religious service in Arlington National Cemetery to honor Indian war dead this weekend despite a ban against it by the United States Army.  The Army's position was upheld yesterday by Judge Howard F. Corcoran of the United States District Court.</p>

<p>The Indians appealed this decision today before the United States Court of Appeals of the District of Columbia.  The appeals court heard arguments this afternoon and said that it would make a ruling tomorrow.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="p21"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi>  <hi rend="italic">  New York Times</hi>, November 06, 1972, p. 21.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Indians Ask Nixon to Solve Impasse</head>
<head type="sub">Reject Government's Offer to Shift to Auditorium</head>

<p>Indians occupying the Bureau of Indian Affairs building urged President Nixon tonight to help find a solution in the impasse between the demonstrators and Federal officials, who have given the Indians an ultimatum to evacuate by tomorrow morning.</p>

<p>Dennis Banks, field director for the American Indian Movement, said the Indians were rejecting the latest overture from the Government, an offer of an interdepartmental auditorium--the same facility proffered repeatedly in the last four days--with showers added.</p>

<p>Mr. Banks said that if the Indians had agreed to move into the auditorium, Federal officials would have arranged an appointment for them with Rogers C. B. Morton, Secretary of the Interior.</p>

<p>About 200 Indians took over the Bureau of Indian Affairs building last Thursday as part of a protest against alleged grievances over the Government's treatment of Indians.  The number inside the building yesterday was put at about 350.</p>

<p><head type="sub">No New Talks</head></p>

<p>Mr. Banks said no new negotiations were planned, and that appointments the Indians said had been arranged by John D. Ehrlichman, the President's assistant for domestic affairs, have been canceled.  He said the Indians did not know the reason, but an Interior Department spokesman said the appointments were never arranged.</p>

<p>"Both this Administration and our caravan are backed up against the election," Mr. Banks said.  "Zero hour is too close to provide meaningful discussion."  He added:</p>

<p>"The Government wants this building, they don't care about us.</p>

<p>The Indians policy council met for 45 minutes tonight to consider the latest offer from the Federal negotiators.</p>

<p>During that time, they refined the wording of the telegram they were sending to Mr. Nixon.  It asks him to appoint a special 12-member committee to oversee the situation, including five Government representatives and seven Indians.</p>

<p>It also asks that a meeting of the commission be convened by Mr. Nixon by no later than 8 A.M. tomorrow, the newest deadline for evacuation of the building.  The President is at the Western White House in San Clemerte, Calif.</p>

<p>A Government spokesman said after offering the latest proposal that, if the Indians rejected it, a Federal judge would be asked to sign a contempt order giving marshals authority to eject the demonstrators from the building.</p>

<p>Vernon Bellecourt, national coordinator of the American Indian Movement, told newsmen earlier tonight that Mr. Ehrlichman and Mr. Garment had agreed to meet with the Indians.  The Government said no such meeting had been arranged.</p>

<p>The Indians have demanded speedy revision of their treaties with the Government, reforms in their ownership and control of land and natural resources and the dismissal of three top Federal officials who deal with Indian problems.</p>

<p>On another issue, the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia reversed a lower court's ruling that would have prohibited the Indians from holding religious services in Arlington National Cemetery to honor Indian war dead there.  The appeals court stayed the effect of its ruling until tomorrow to allow the Government time to appeal the case to the Supreme Court if it wished.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="p73"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi>  <hi rend="italic">  New York Times</hi>, November 07, 1972, p. 73.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Eviction of Indians Delayed on Appeal</head>

<p>A Federal judge gave the Government permission today to retake the Bureau of Indian Affairs building from militant Indians, but a Federal appeals court stayed the order until Wednesday.</p>

<p>The stay prevented a possible clash between the police and the Indians, who were prepared to fight for the building that they have occupied since last Thursday.</p>

<p>The United States Court of Appeals issued its stay order a few hours after Judge H. Pratt of the United States District Court held the protesters in contempt of court and gave the Government authority to evict them.</p>

<p>The three-judge appeals court delayed enforcement of Judge Pratt's order until 9 P.M. Wednesday, and directed that negotiations between the Indians and Government officials continue.</p>

<p>Judge Pratt had said that the Indians had "flagrantly violated" a temporary restraining order he issued last week directing them to vacate the property.  Counsel for the Indians carried their appeal to the higher court.</p>

<p>Federal officials were not unhappy with the appeals court order.  While believing that the Indians would have to be ousted by force eventually, they felt that any action should be held up until after tomorrow's election.</p>

<p>At the Indian Affairs bureau, the protesters, numbering about 500, appeared to be making preparations against any attempt to dislodge them.  Many of them were armed with improvised clubs and spears made of knives lashed to poles.  Some had smeared their faces with lipstick in simulation of war paint.</p>

<p><head type="sub">'Any Weapons'</head></p>

<p>Russell Means, a leader of the protest, said that 200 Indians had taken a vow to fight to the death.  The Indians will use, he said, "any weapons we can lay our hands on" but said that none of the group had any firearms.</p>

<p>Mr. Means, 32 years old, is a national field director of the American Indian Movement, which has led young activist Indians in protests against "broken treaties and promises" that they say have stalled Indian efforts to gain greater economic educational, health and other benefits.</p>

<p>They have also protested against the conflict within the Department of the Interior, of which the bureau is a part, over taking Indian lands for water and mineral resources and called for the bureau to be set up under separate control of Indians.</p>

<p>Secretary of the Interior Rogers C. B. Morton described the protesters tonight as a "splinter group of militants."</p>

<p>"It is obvious to me that the seizure and continued occupation of the building are nothing more than a form of blackmail by a small group which seek to achieve through violence objectives which are not supported by a majority of reservation Indians," he said in a statement.</p>

<p>The White House had overruled any effort to evict the Indians pending the outcome of negotiations with Federal officials and a final court decision.  Some Interior officials had sought immediate action against the protesters when they seized the building Thursday night.</p>

<p>The Indians deliberately chose the eve of the Presidential election to dramatize their demands.  They sought unsuccessfully to meet with President Nixon and his top aides.</p>

<p>They named their caravan to Washington "The Trail of Broken Treaties."  The main body comes by bus, station wagons and car across the country from the West Coast, picking up adherents along the way.  Anther caravan came from North Carolina.</p>

<p>This morning, as the Government went back to court to get an eviction order, Vernon Bellecourt, a director of A.I.M., told the militants, "We have now declared war on the United States of America--see your stations.</p>

<p>A few women and children remained in the building at 20th Street and Constitution Avenue, a few blocks from the White House, but most of them had been removed to housing arranged by volunteers.  A tepee was set up on the building grounds facing Constitution Avenue, and Indian guards patrolled outside and inside the six-story structure.</p>

<p><head type="sub">No Time Set</head></p>

<p>Judge Pratt made his order effective at 6 P.M. but left it up to the Government when to enforce the order.</p>

<p>"The Government is going to retake that building and as soon as the Indians comply, the better off they will be," he said.</p>

<p>James Heller, an attorney for the Indians, sought more time for negotiations with Government officials who have met periodically for five days over the demands.</p>

<p>"Time is something we have," Mr. Heller said.  "Blood is something we can't afford."</p>

<p>The choice, he said, was between minor property damage and "the dreadful possibility of bloodshed."</p>

<p>Judge Pratt issued his initial restraining order directing the Indians to leave the building last Friday but directed that Indian Affairs Bureau and Interior Department officials continue to negotiate.</p>

<p>The Indians demanded, in addition to immediate executive and Congressional actions on new treaties and land reform, housing and other accomodations during their stay.  The Government countered with--and the Indians rejected--a Federal auditorium nearby and trailers for sanitary facilities but no food or financial assistance.</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="p49"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi>  <hi rend="italic">  New York Times</hi>, November 08, 1972, p. 49.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Militant Indians Agree to Leave</head>

<p>Militant Indians agreed tonight to evacuate the Bureau of Indian Affairs building, which they have held for six days.</p>

<p>The agreement was reached with White House negotiators who offered a program for dealing with Indian grievances.  The Indians are expected to leave the building at 9 A.M. tomorrow.  They barricaded the six-story structure last Thursday, forcing the Government to suspend bureau operations.</p>

<p>The agreement with the Indians included the naming of a Federal study group that will make recommendations to President Nixon.</p>

<p>Facing the deadline of a Federal court order to leave the building by tomorrow night or be evicted by force, the Indians accepted a broad program offered by Presidential aides to hear Indian grievances and proposals for more economic, educational and social aid.</p>

<p>The Federal study group will include officers of 13 Federal departments and agencies dealing with Indian affairs, including the White House and the office of the Vice President.  It will be a continuing body for six months and will make a report to President Nixon by next June 1.</p>

<p>The peace pact was worked out in sessions that began at noon with leaders of the "trial of broken treaties" protestors.  The Indians barricaded themselves in the building last Thursday and threatened to meet force with force.</p>

<p>The White House took control of the negotiations after a series of fruitless talks between the Indians and officials of the Interior Department, parent body of the Bureau of Indian Affairs.</p>

<p>About 100 of the 500 Indians who invaded the building were reported to be still holding the structure tonight.  Most of the elderly Indians and women and children who had accompanied the protesters had been removed to private housing.  Some of the younger Indians were seen leaving the structure this afternoon.</p>

<p>The agreement was worked out by Frank Carlucci, deputy director of the Office of Management and Budget; Leonard Garment, special consultant to the President for minority affairs, and Louis R. Bruce, Commissioner of Indian Affairs.  Mr. Carlucci and Mr. Garment will be co-chairmen of the study group.</p>

<p>The eight Indian negotiators were headed by Hank Adams, an Assinaboine from Puyallup, Wash., who has been an activist in the fight for Indian rights.  A lawyer, he has been a leader of the American Indian Movement, the moving force behind the protest here.</p>

<p>Under terms of the agreement, all proposals submitted by the militants will be considered, but the Federal panel will "follow an open access, no exclusion, no preference policy and will seek an input from a cross-section of the Indian community."</p>

<p><head type="sub">Main Points Cited</head></p>

<p>The agreement, a statement said, emphasizes:</p>

<p>- "Eligibility of various Indian groups for governmental services."  This appeared to be a concession to the protesters who contended that urban Indians living off reservations were neglected by Federal agencies.</p>

<p>- "The adequacy of governmental organizational structure to coordinate programs and services for Indians."  The protesters had called for abolition of the Bureau of Indian Affairs and for its functions to be put in the White House.</p>

<p>- "The quality, speed and effectiveness or the delivery of Federal programs to all Indian people."</p>

<p>- "Issues concerning fairness in institutions and practices of Indian self-government."</p>

<p>- "Appropriate and proper means to insure Congressional implementation of necessary Indian legislation."</p>

<p>Establishment of the panel came after the United States Court of Appeals here delayed a deadline for the Indians to get out of the building or face eviction by the Federal authorities until tomorrow at 9 P.M.  The court said there would be no extension of the deadline after that time.</p>

<p>Judge John H. Pratt of the United States District Court thority to evict the Indians by 6 P.M. yesterday.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="p52"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi>  <hi rend="italic">  New York Times</hi>, November 09, 1972, p. 52.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Indians Take Documents as They Leave U.S. Building</head>

<p>Loaded with what they called "incriminating" documents purloined from Federal files, Indian militants began leaving the Bureau of Indian Affairs Building today.  They took over the building a week ago.</p>

<p>Federal officials reported late tonight that the building had been cleared and would be sealed until tomorrow when security forces would inspect it.  They said that the Indians had left before a court-imposed deadline of 9 P.M. when the Government would have been free to force them out.</p>

<p>The Indians began to leave the building soon after reaching an agreement with White House aides on review of their grievances.  Also agreed on were proposed solutions to Indian problems.  These problems include century-old treaty rights, education, economic opportunities and self-determination in the white man's world.</p>

<p>Presidential assistants agreed to create a special Federal body, headed by the White House, to come up with recommendations to be presented to President Nixon by June 1, 1973.</p>

<p><head type="sub">Given Financial Aid</head></p>

<p>The Indians were granted financial assistance to return to their homes.  Federal officials said that $60,000 in Government funds had been made available to assist the Indians.</p>

<p>The initial payments were made to Indians who left the building tonight.  Indian leaders distributed the money as the Indians passed through the building auditorium.  The money was in piles of bills that appeared to be of $100 denominations.</p>

<p>Dennis Banks, a spokesman for the Indians self-styled "Trail of Broken Treaties," said the protesters had collected at least two truckloads of "highly incriminating evidence" on Indian affairs against present and past members of Congress.</p>

<p>"Four of us have got the documents," he told reporters.  He said that the documents had been "safely removed from the country" and that "we are going to get legal assistance to see wht justice we can get."</p>

<p>"The evidence is highly incriminating against two or three ex-Senators from Western states," he said, adding that judging from what they had found in Federal reports "we could nail down four or five Congressmen."</p>

<p>He said that some of the documents included reports from the Federal Bureau of Investigation but he did not elaborate.</p>

<p>"We have destroyed the B.I.A.," he said.</p>

<p>Throughout the day, groups of Indians could be seen leaving the six-story structure, carrying rolled-up paintings and other Indian art that had been in display in the building.  Policemen in plainsclothes made no effort to stop them.</p>

<p>The Indians had dwindled to about 100 within the building.  They numbered about 500 at one time.  Most of the women and children and elderly persons who had accompanied the protesters moved two days ago to donated private housings.</p>

<p>Interior officials said the building had been looted.  No only of files, but of "priceless Indian art and artifacts."  Until the end of the occupation, newsmen were not permitted to enter the structure, which Federal authorities said was heavily damaged.</p>

<p>The Indians broke up furniture and other equipment to fashing clubs and spears and other weapons against a threatened Federal take-over.</p>

<p>Officials of the Department of the Interior, of which the Indian Bureau is a part, issued orders that only authorized personnel would be allowed in the building after the Indians had gone.  The first step in regaining the building, they said, was for a thorough shake-down of the building by a "bomb squad" to make certain the Indians had not planted explosives or other devices in an effort to destroy it.</p>

<p>Mr. Banks is a field director of the American Indian Movement, the backbone of the protest here.  The organization itself has been wracked by internal dissention in the last year but Mr. Banks has managed to maintain a major position among the militants.</p>

<p>In a final negotiating session with Federal officials today, the Indians won a pledge that the White House aides would recommend that the government not prosecute the Indians who took over the building last Thursday.</p>

<p>When the Indians arrived in caravans from the West Coast and the South last week they faced shortages of food, housing and funds, which they demanded from the Government.  Turned down at first, they took over the building's auditorium.  In succeeding days, officials withdrew from the building and began a series of fruitless negotiations that ended when the White House took over mediation on Monday night.  Food and other supplies were brought into the building by Indian and white sympathizers.</p>

<p>Earlier, the Government won an eviction order from Judge John H. Pratt of the United States District Court here, but he ordered the negotiations to continue.  The United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia stayed Judge Pratt's eviction order from last night until tonight to give the Government time to end the deadlock.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="p17"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi>  <hi rend="italic">  New York Times</hi>, November 10, 1972, p. 17.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Indians Take Documents as They Leave U.S. Building</head>
<head type="sub">Bureau is Found Littered by Debris After Protest</head>

	<p>Militant American Indians left behind them today a battered Bureau of Indian Affairs Building that may take months to restore to usefulness.</p>

	<p>Before they left the building last night--after reaching an agreement with the Government to end their six-day takeover of the building--they wrecked nearly every piece of furniture and office equipment from typewriters to sensitive computers and spray-painted graffiti on walls.</p>

	<p>Among the graffiti were the names of tribes and individuals--"Fighting Cheyenne," "Towa, Pueblo, N.M.," Seneca" and "Benjamin Bear, Tama, Iowa."</p>

	<p>Four floors of the building were carpeted with broken glass, empty food tins, paper from rifled filing cabinets and other debris.  Fire hoses trailed out of smashed cabinets.  Fixtures in some restrooms were smashed.  And the stench of rotting food pervaded the ground floor near the wrecked cafeteria.</p>

	<p>Picture frames from which Indian paintings had been taken were torn apart.  A large display cabinet that had housed priceless Indian artifacts was smashed, and the artifacts taken.  At least two valuable Navajo rugs were missing.</p>

<p>The office of Indian Commissioner Louis R. Bruce, an Oglala Sioux and Mohawk from New York, was ripped up.  Leather sofas and chairs were slashed by a sharp instrument, as were similar pieces in other offices.  The militants had used Mr. Bruce's office as a command post.  A half-eaten jar of peanut butter was on his stratched desk.</p>

<p>Containers of gasoline were found in the building's auditorium, where the Indians gathered initially and began making demands on the Government for housing and food.</p>

<p>Officials estimated that the takeover would cost the Government $1-million or more.</p>

<p>Some members of the National Tribal Chairmen's Association, which is made up of elected leaders of the country's 750,000 Indians on reservations, toured the building and expressed shock.</p>

<p>A group of Congressional aides, representing the Interior and Appropriations Committees in the Senate and House, also inspected the damage and heard the tribal leaders call for an investigation and prosecution of militants who they contend are mainly urban activists.</p>

<p><head type="sub">U.S. Officials Blamed</head></p>

<p>Webster Two Hawk, president of the Chairmen's Association and chairman of the Rosebud Sioux Tribal Council of South Dakota, blamed Government officials for "a bungling of this whole thing by allowing them [the militants] to dig in."</p>

<p>"If they go scot free, they'll be back," said Robert Him, chairman of the Yakima tribal council of Toppenish, Wash.  He said that the tribes were particularly concerned over the destruction and theft of treaty, land and other documents that record vital negotiations on Indian rights and aid.</p>

<p>"If this can happen on a Federal lelve, it can happen on a local level," he said.  "Congress and the Federal Government should not stand for this criminal action."</p>

<p>The agreement worked out by White House aides promised that no one would be prosecuted for occupation of the building.  But, Federal officials emphasized, this proviso does not extend to damage or theft, which will have to be assessed before any legal action can be instituted.</p>

		<p>The peace pact called for creation of a speical inter-agency panel covering a dozen departments and agencies dealing in Indian affairs.  The panel will discuss with the country's entire Indian community grievances put forward by the Indians.  The Indians seek revision of treaties, land reform and speedier Federal action on water, mineral and other rights that they contend are being exploited by white men.</p>

<p>The Federal Government also gave the protesters $60,000 to help them to get home or meet other needs, but what had happened to the sum was not clear today.  Some of the money was passed out last night at the Indian Affairs Bureau by militant leaders.</p>

<p>The money was channeled to the American Indian Movement through the National Congress of American Indians.  Charles E. Trimble, director of the congress, said today that the organization was not responsible for dispensing the money, which, he said, was given to militant leaders in a lump sum.</p>

<p>"The prime consideration was not to get the Indians out of town," he said.  "It was to aid the stranded or sick."</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="p49"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi>  <hi rend="italic">  New York Times</hi>, November 08, 1972, p. 49.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Militant Indians Agree to Leave</head>

<p>Militant Indians agreed tonight to evacuate the Bureau of Indian Affairs building, which they have held for six days.</p>

<p>The agreement was reached with White House negotiators who offered a program for dealing with Indian grievances.  The Indians are expected to leave the building at 9 A.M. tomorrow.  They barricaded the six-story structure last Thursday, forcing the Government to suspend bureau operations.</p>

<p>The agreement with the Indians included the naming of a Federal study group that will make recommendations to President Nixon.</p>

<p>Facing the deadline of a Federal court order to leave the building by tomorrow night or be evicted by force, the Indians accepted a broad program offered by Presidential aides to hear Indian grievances and proposals for more economic, educational and social aid.</p>

<p>The Federal study group will include officers of 13 Federal departments and agencies dealing with Indian affairs, including the White House and the office of the Vice President.  It will be a continuing body for six months and will make a report to President Nixon by next June 1.</p>

<p>The peace pact was worked out in sessions that began at noon with leaders of the "trial of broken treaties" protestors.  The Indians barricaded themselves in the building last Thursday and threatened to meet force with force.</p>

<p>The White House took control of the negotiations after a series of fruitless talks between the Indians and officials of the Interior Department, parent body of the Bureau of Indian Affairs.</p>

<p>About 100 of the 500 Indians who invaded the building were reported to be still holding the structure tonight.  Most of the elderly Indians and women and children who had accompanied the protesters had been removed to private housing.  Some of the younger Indians were seen leaving the structure this afternoon.</p>

<p>The agreement was worked out by Frank Carlucci, deputy director of the Office of Management and Budget; Leonard Garment, special consultant to the President for minority affairs, and Louis R. Bruce, Commissioner of Indian Affairs.  Mr. Carlucci and Mr. Garment will be co-chairmen of the study group.</p>

<p>The eight Indian negotiators were headed by Hank Adams, an Assinaboine from Puyallup, Wash., who has been an activist in the fight for Indian rights.  A lawyer, he has been a leader of the American Indian Movement, the moving force behind the protest here.</p>

<p>Under terms of the agreement, all proposals submitted by the militants will be considered, but the Federal panel will "follow an open access, no exclusion, no preference policy and will seek an input from a cross-section of the Indian community."</p>

<p><head type="sub">Main Points Cited</head></p>

<p>The agreement, a statement said, emphasizes:</p>

<p>- "Eligibility of various Indian groups for governmental services."  This appeared to be a concession to the protesters who contended that urban Indians living off reservations were neglected by Federal agencies.</p>

<p>- "The adequacy of governmental organizational structure to coordinate programs and services for Indians."  The protesters had called for abolition of the Bureau of Indian Affairs and for its functions to be put in the White House.</p>

<p>- "The quality, speed and effectiveness or the delivery of Federal programs to all Indian people."</p>

<p>- "Issues concerning fairness in institutions and practices of Indian self-government."</p>

<p>- "Appropriate and proper means to insure Congressional implementation of necessary Indian legislation."</p>

<p>Establishment of the panel came after the United States Court of Appeals here delayed a deadline for the Indians to get out of the building or face eviction by the Federal authorities until tomorrow at 9 P.M.  The court said there would be no extension of the deadline after that time.</p>

<p>Judge John H. Pratt of the United States District Court thority to evict the Indians by 6 P.M. yesterday.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="p52"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi>  <hi rend="italic">  New York Times</hi>, November 09, 1972, p. 52.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Indians Take Documents as They Leave U.S. Building</head>

<p>Loaded with what they called "incriminating" documents purloined from Federal files, Indian militants began leaving the Bureau of Indian Affairs Building today.  They took over the building a week ago.</p>

<p>Federal officials reported late tonight that the building had been cleared and would be sealed until tomorrow when security forces would inspect it.  They said that the Indians had left before a court-imposed deadline of 9 P.M. when the Government would have been free to force them out.</p>

<p>The Indians began to leave the building soon after reaching an agreement with White House aides on review of their grievances.  Also agreed on were proposed solutions to Indian problems.  These problems include century-old treaty rights, education, economic opportunities and self-determination in the white man's world.</p>

<p>Presidential assistants agreed to create a special Federal body, headed by the White House, to come up with recommendations to be presented to President Nixon by June 1, 1973.</p>

<p><head type="sub">Given Financial Aid</head></p>

<p>The Indians were granted financial assistance to return to their homes.  Federal officials said that $60,000 in Government funds had been made available to assist the Indians.</p>

<p>The initial payments were made to Indians who left the building tonight.  Indian leaders distributed the money as the Indians passed through the building auditorium.  The money was in piles of bills that appeared to be of $100 denominations.</p>

<p>Dennis Banks, a spokesman for the Indians self-styled "Trail of Broken Treaties," said the protesters had collected at least two truckloads of "highly incriminating evidence" on Indian affairs against present and past members of Congress.</p>

<p>"Four of us have got the documents," he told reporters.  He said that the documents had been "safely removed from the country" and that "we are going to get legal assistance to see wht justice we can get."</p>

<p>"The evidence is highly incriminating against two or three ex-Senators from Western states," he said, adding that judging from what they had found in Federal reports "we could nail down four or five Congressmen."</p>

<p>He said that some of the documents included reports from the Federal Bureau of Investigation but he did not elaborate.</p>

<p>"We have destroyed the B.I.A.," he said.</p>

<p>Throughout the day, groups of Indians could be seen leaving the six-story structure, carrying rolled-up paintings and other Indian art that had been in display in the building.  Policemen in plainsclothes made no effort to stop them.</p>

<p>The Indians had dwindled to about 100 within the building.  They numbered about 500 at one time.  Most of the women and children and elderly persons who had accompanied the protesters moved two days ago to donated private housings.</p>

<p>Interior officials said the building had been looted.  No only of files, but of "priceless Indian art and artifacts."  Until the end of the occupation, newsmen were not permitted to enter the structure, which Federal authorities said was heavily damaged.</p>

<p>The Indians broke up furniture and other equipment to fashing clubs and spears and other weapons against a threatened Federal take-over.</p>

<p>Officials of the Department of the Interior, of which the Indian Bureau is a part, issued orders that only authorized personnel would be allowed in the building after the Indians had gone.  The first step in regaining the building, they said, was for a thorough shake-down of the building by a "bomb squad" to make certain the Indians had not planted explosives or other devices in an effort to destroy it.</p>

<p>Mr. Banks is a field director of the American Indian Movement, the backbone of the protest here.  The organization itself has been wracked by internal dissention in the last year but Mr. Banks has managed to maintain a major position among the militants.</p>

<p>In a final negotiating session with Federal officials today, the Indians won a pledge that the White House aides would recommend that the government not prosecute the Indians who took over the building last Thursday.</p>

<p>When the Indians arrived in caravans from the West Coast and the South last week they faced shortages of food, housing and funds, which they demanded from the Government.  Turned down at first, they took over the building's auditorium.  In succeeding days, officials withdrew from the building and began a series of fruitless negotiations that ended when the White House took over mediation on Monday night.  Food and other supplies were brought into the building by Indian and white sympathizers.</p>

<p>Earlier, the Government won an eviction order from Judge John H. Pratt of the United States District Court here, but he ordered the negotiations to continue.  The United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia stayed Judge Pratt's eviction order from last night until tonight to give the Government time to end the deadlock.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="pA8"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Washington Post</hi>, October 19, 1972, p. A8.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">300 Indians Protest Proposed Fund Cut</head>

<p>The leader of the American Indian Movement says "it may take another Watts" before the United States realizes "the plight of the American Indians."</p>

<p>The reference to racial disorders which shook the Watts section of Los Angeles in the 1960s was made by Dennis Banks, as some 300 Indians traveled what AIM leaders call the "trail of broken treaties" to Washington D.C. to protest proposed cuts in the budget of the Bureau of Indian Affairs.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="pC1"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Washington Post</hi>, October 31, 1972, p. C1.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Indians Converging on D.C. for Rallies</head>

<p>Proclaiming, "We come here in peace," leaders of a coalition of 250 of the nation's 300 American Indian tribes began converging in Washington yesterday for a week of activities aimed at dramatizing the traditions and the needs of their people.</p>

<p>Sixty-five Indians, the first contingent of what leaders of the "Trail of Broken Treaties" caravan say may swell to more than 5,000 Indians by the weekend, arrived after a cross-country trip that began Oct. 2 in Los Angeles, San Francisco and Seattle and wound through reservations along the way.</p>

<p>"We want to meet with the people who represent us, and we want to show Americans what our culture is all about," said Robert Burnette, former tribal chairman of the Rosebud Sioux tribe in Mission, S.D., and "Trails" group co-chairman.</p>

<p>Burnette said Indian leaders had sought meetings with President Nixon and Sen. George McGovern.  He said McGovern has agreed to a meeting, possibly today, and that the White House had ruled out a meeting with the President but was arranging for an Interior Department official to meet with the Indian leaders.</p>

<p>At the meetings--and in position papers to be aired during the week--the Indians are scheduled to call for fulfillment of all U.S. treaty obligations with Indian tribes and for protection of Indian rights to water, minerals and land.</p>

<p>There are about 840,000 Indians in the United States today.  Approximately half of them live in reservations.</p>

<p>Another concern to be voiced is a continuing quest by Indian leaders to have the Interior Department's Bureau of Indian Affairs replaced with the federal Indian commission.</p>

<p>Indian activists have charged that the bureau of Indian affairs has become a dumping ground for incompetent government workers, while maintaining that the agency is "insensitive" to the concerns of Indians.</p>

<p>The demonstrators say they also plan to ask both presidential candidates for commitments for increased funds and a referendum of all Indian tribes each time the government wants to cut a tribe off from service.</p>

<p>"The caravan itself may lack the dramatic character that draws public attention at this stage," conceded Sid Mills, a 24-year-old Yakima Indian from Frank Landing, Wash., who is coordinating the car caravan.</p>

<p>"Nonetheless, we believe that it can be the beginning of an educational process among Indian people which can produce a reasoned, rational--revolutionary, if you will--manifesto for construction of an Indian future in America."</p>

<p>Indian activism--almost unheard of until the late 1960s--has been blossoming since 1969, when two apparently unrelated events occured, one quietly, the other under the glare of photographers' and television cameras.</p>

<p>Early in the year, the American Indian Movement, the organization that many leaders credit with awakening a then-dormant sense of pride among Indians, was quietly founded by Russell Means, an Ogalala Sioux from South Dakota.</p>

<p>And, on the night of Nov. 20, 1969, a group of 78 Indians from 30 tribes invaded the island of Alcatraz, a 21-acre rock a mile offshore in San Francisco.  Their claim to ownership of the island was rejected by the U.S. government, and the squatters remained on the rock for several months before being rejected.</p>

<p>But their action triggered a series of similar "invasions" of disputed sites, some of which resulted in successes for the Indians.</p>

<p>That was the case with a surplus 640-acre Army site near Davis, Calif., which an Indian group wanted to use to establish a university for Indians and Mexican-Americans.</p>

<p>The government, although rejecting the Indians' claim to the property, issued a permit entrusting to them the "custody, protection and maintenance" of the site.</p>

<p>The caravan will be the latest rallying point for airing Indian grievances, Mills said.</p>

<p>"Current programs are not keeping pace with growing problems, and are eliminating virtually none," he said.  "Obviously, prospects for change are not good unless the caravan insists upon new and different solutions than are presently being applied."</p>

<p>Burnette said a contingent of 800 participants will arrive in Washington today after a swing through Minnesota, Indiana, Ohio and North Carolina.  Another 1,500 demonstrators are expected Wednesday and smaller groups will arrive during the rest of the week, he said.</p>

<p>The demonstrators, who will be housed at several area churches and private homes, will begin a series of meetings and religous services Thursday, Burnette said during a press conference at the Bureau of Indian Affairs auditorium yesterday morning.</p>

<p>Their activities will include a parade around the White House at 9:30 a.m. Saturday, and will conclude with a general assembly at the Sylvan Theater on the Washington Monument ground's at 10 a.m. Monday.</p>

<p>The group has been authorized by the U.S. Park Police to erect about 30 "symbolic" tee-pees in Potomac Park West, on the banks of the Potomac River.</p>

<p>The traditional Indian habitats will be occupied by "medicine men" from various tribes during the day, but will not be used as sleeping quarters, a police spokesman said.  A group of trail representatives has been authorized to stand guard on the site at night.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="pA1"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi>  <hi rend="italic">  Washington Post</hi>, November 03, 1972, p. A1.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">500 Indians Here Seize U.S. Building</head>

<p>At least 500 Indians barricaded themselves inside the Bureau of Indian Affairs building yesterday evening in the first day of the planned week of protests that organizers had said would be peaceful.</p>

<p>The Indians, who represent a coalition of 250 of the nation's 300 tribes, blocked all entrances to the building at 19th Street and Constitution Avenue NW and draped it with American flags.</p>

<p>They said they were renaming the building "The Native American Embassy."</p>

<p>Shortly before midnight, an Indian spokesman told reporters that an agreement had been reached in a 2-hour meeting with officials from the White House and the BIA permitting the Indians to remain overnight.</p>

<p>The spokesman, Russell Means, said that the demonstrators would leave this morning and had been promised accommodation in other government buildings or local churches for the duration of their stay.</p>

<p>A force of hundreds of riot-equipped police from the Federal Protective Service that had been stationed in the nearby Interior Department was withdrawn.  Officials said there would be no attempt to clear the building.</p>

<p>The Indians seized it after a day of heated discussions with government officials about housing facilities for the coming week and the locations of organized demonstrations the Indians intend to hold.</p>

<p>Calling themselves the "Trail of Broken Treaties" caravan, Indians have been arriving in Washington since Monday and planned to begin yesterday a series of services, workshops and other activities to dramatize their traditions and needs.</p>

<p><!--continues on p. A24, col. 1-->The Indian leaders said they were hoping that several thousand persons would eventually be part of the caravan.  There are now about 800,000 Indians in the United States and their interests in Washington are overseen by the Interior Department's Bureau of Indian Affairs.</p>

<p>In recent years, as the tone of Indian discontent has become more strident, much of the criticism has been directed at the BIA.  Abolition of the bureau, spokesmen said, was one of the prime purposes of the activities here.</p>

<p>Instead, the issues have become obscured in disputes over permits and lodging.  Most of yesterday's activities were canceled while Indians milled about the Bureau of Indian Affairs building waiting for the outcome of the negotiations with officials.</p>

<p>The Indians arrived at the building in the morning sand throughout the day said they were "occupying" it.  But business in the offices went on almost as usual and all entrances remained open.</p>

<p>Shortly before 5 p.m., a brief clash developed between guards and Indian youths.  The cause of the disturbance was not clear, but a reporter saw the Indians arguing with one group of security men at a downstairs exit and moments later fighting and another group of guards.</p>

<p>On [sic] Indian spokesman said at least six of the protesters were clubbed by security police.  The spokesmen said that four of the Indians were arrested, but police said they had decided to neither hold nor charge any of the protesters.</p>

<p>As word of the fight spread, Indians began breaking into offices and dragging furniture into the hallways.  The police were forced to back out of the building and remained outside while the barricades were being erected.</p>

<p>The Indians, most of whom are young, hauled tables, couches, lockers and machinery out of the offices, scattering shattered glass from the locked doors they had broken down.</p>

<p>But in keeping with their effort to maintain control of the situation, the Indian leaders directed the demonstrators to clean up the debris, which they did.</p>

<p>At least a dozen BIA officials were trapped inside the building, but none was menaced by the protesters and all managed to leave, exiting through windows and fire escapes, employees later told reporters.</p>

<p>Just as the outburst was erupting, in another part of the building Indian spokesmen were holding a press conference to tell of an agreement that had been reached on accommodations.</p>

<p>The Indians had been offered use of the BIA building and the massive Departmental Auditorium, the spokesman said.</p>

<p>Dennis Banks, national field director of the American Indian Movement and coordinator of the "Trail of Broken Treaties," told reporters that the Indian leadership was "still amazed at the hostile attitude of government officials."</p>

<p>He said that while the question of housing had been resolved, no progress had been made on the request for permission to hold a service at Arlington National Cemetery.  The request had been denied by the Army and the Indians have filed a suit in U.S. District Court that will be heard at 11 a.m. today.</p>

<p>"Only going through federal court," Banks said, "will we be able to hold religious services for Indian people who died serving in wars for this country."</p>

<p>As a result of the haggling over facilities and what Banks said was an attitude on the part of officials to "keep the Indians down," he promised a "stepped-up tempo" to the protests.</p>

<p>As Banks finished, the shouts from the skirmish a floor below attracted an unruly crowd of Indians, reporters and guards.  Banks said later, after talking with those at the scene, that the security force had misunderstood the agreement reached with officials and thought there was to be "a confrontation with the Indians."</p>

<p>While his supporters were ranging about the building, Banks told reporters that the dispute was the guards' fault.  "I can see why we have police riots in this country," he said.  "We have had an overreaction by untrained personnel."</p>

<p>Before last night's outburst, the mood of the Indian demonstrators had been restive but orderly.  Most of them had congregated in the BIA auditorium chanting Indian songs, watching movies, and sleeping and eating.</p>

<p>Indians hold a unique place among American minorities because of the existence of a federal agency intended solely to deal with their problems.  The Bureau of Indian Affairs, now headquartered in the imposing four-story building at 19th Street and Constitution Avenue, was created in 1824 and became part of the Interior Department in 1849.</p>

<p>With a budget of about $300 million, the bureau coordinates a variety of educational, social welfare and development programs.  In recent years, BIA has experienced a surge of innovative spirit, which observers credited to the pressures for change coming from the Indians.</p>

<p>Nonetheless, Indians are still calling for abolition of the bureau and creation of a new agency more responsive to their needs.</p>

<p>The Indians have issued a list of 20 demands that they want met, including a number of treaty adjustments and land reforms.  The details of the demands are complex, but a number of interviews yesterday showed that emotions underlying them are simple.</p>

<p>"We will no longer be put down," said Jerry Rogers, a 28-year-old Chippewa.  "We will no longer be shoved off into a back corner.  We want what we want.  And we remember that before the whie man came we lived in peace."</p>

<p>By seizing the building yesterday, the Indians managed to receive the top-level attention their protest had been designed to attract.  Brad Patterson, the White Hosue special assitant for Indian affairs, assured the Indian leaders, a spokesman said, that their 20 demands would receive point-by-point written responses.</p>

<p>Patterson also told the Indians, according to their spokesman, that they would be given appointments with anyone they requested.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="pA8"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Washington Post</hi>, November 4, 1972, p. A8.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">'Indians First, Always,' Demonstrator Declares</head>

<p>The hundreds of young Indians ranging through the government-drab corridors of the Bureau of Indian Affairs these past two days share the exuberance of radical pride and anger over the age-old suffering of their people.</p>

<p>"We are Indians first and always," said 16-year-old Morgan Grass, a Cherokee Ponca.</p>

<p>The long hair, beads and rough-hewn clothes they wear are not just an identification with the mode of present-day America, but also a link to the past, to the costumes of their Indian forebears.</p>

<p>Even their slogans mix modern militance with sagas of another time: "Indian Power," "Geronimo was right," "Custer had it coming and so do some others."</p>

<p>Martha Grass, the mother of Morgan and a proud Cherokee herself, took a measure of the scene Thursday afternoon, as the Indians barricaded themselves in the building, and said:</p>

<p>"It's for these youngsters to take us back to Indian ways.  They're the ones that can say 'now we will take care of ourselves.'  The older people are just beat.  They don't think change is possible."</p>

<p>The 800,000 Indians in the United States have a heritage of special agony that they say sets them apart from other minorities.  Most of their land has been taken, their numbers have dwindled and many of their customs have become tourist caricatures.</p>

<p>The beating tom-toms, the chants and dances of the young in the auditorium of the Indian Affairs building will bring back neither land nor brothers, but they revive the spirit and remind all who listen of former Indian glories.</p>

<p>The Indians who came to Washington this week on what they call "The Trail of Broken Treaties," have traveled long distances, from Nebraska, Oklahoma, Kansas and North Carolina, the organizers claim 5,000 will come; so far, it is closer to 1,000.</p>

<p>Their leaders, mostly from the organized American Indian Movement, are smooth and experienced in the ways of protest, comfortable in the televised glare of press conferences, adept with crowd-calling bullhorns and tough in the closed-door negotiations with the officials they have come to challenge.</p>

<p>Peter La Pointe, a 42-year-old Winnebago Sioux who is the Nebraska state coordinator for the AIM, said the purpose of the week of demonstrations was "to show that Indians will no longer be at the bottom of the totem pole."</p>

<p>"We demonstrated before 100 years ago when we fought the white man; we lost that," he went on, "but there is a new awakening now.  The black has accomplished his goals.  We want ours."</p>

<p>Those goals are encompassed in a lengthy manifesto of 20 points, a complicated compilation of long-time Indian demands: the right to self-determination and the promise of a richer, better life.</p>

<p>Few of the demonstrators can tell you much about the details of that manifesto.  They talk instead of the white man's prejudice and oppression and their intention to win back what is rightly theirs: not land so much, but dignity.</p>

<p>"This country should let me live as I always did," said Jerry Rogers, a 28-year-old Chippewa laborer, "they shouldn't be telling me to do a lot of things, like fighting wars where we don't belong and going up in space where don't belong either."</p>

<p>For Lydia and Hope Heis, 14 and 16 respectively, the problem takes a different turn.  They are Sioux from Minnesota and until this year went to the public schools.  Now they attend a "red schoolhouse," what they called, "a survival school for Indians."</p>

<p>"We were surrounded by white people in white school," said Lydia.  "It was too much of a hassle because they kept saying they were best and Indians are nothing.  I'm not worried anymore, though, because Indians will get their rights."</p>

<p>Behind the BIA building, in the parking lot crowded with the Indians' cars, three young men sat talking, matching each other in the sharpness of their rhetoric.</p>

<p>One said his name was Len Not-Afriad and he used an American flag to wipe his nose.  "We are prisoners in our own country," he said.  "Who ever gave you white men the right to do that?"</p>

<p>Another youth said he was Joe Moving-Around.  "We are ready to fight and die for what we believe in," he said, "just like the people who lived here 100 years ago."</p>

<p>Len Not-Afraid listened.  "Right on, right on," he said.</p>
	

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="pA1"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Washington Post</hi>, November 4, 1972, p. A1.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Indians Continue Occupation of BIA</head>

<p>Most of a group of 400 protesting Indians, who vowed to remain in the Bureau of Indian Affairs until their demands for "self-determination" are met, continued their second day of occupation of the building early today.</p>

<p>However, about 100 women and children left about 10 p.m. after U.S. marshals served a temporary restraining order, obtained in District Court, that directed the removal of the Indians.</p>

<p>Marshals instructed protestors to go to the Department of Interior Auditorium when they left the BIA.</p>

<p>After deciding that the women and children should be evacuated the remaining protesters voted to stay in the building and began making preparations to defend it against any possible assault.</p>

<p>At 1:30 a.m. talks broke off between marshals and the protesters, who refused offers to stay at the Interdepartmental Auditorium.  However, Interior Department officials had said earlier that in such a case, formal contempt proceedings would be held before any attempt at forcible eviction.</p>

<p>Earlier yesterday, while the restraining order was being issued, Commissioner of Indian Affairs Louis R. Bruce, apparently unaware of the legal action, was negotiationg with Indian leaders to insure their safe stay in the building.</p>

<p>Assistant Interior Secretary Harrison Loesch said that the order by Judge John H. Pratt was precipitated by "the failure of this group to adhere to their announced intentions of peaceful petition."  Loesch said the order had the backing of a number of "responsible and elected" Indian leaders.</p>

<p>In another court action yesterday, District Court Judge Howard Corcoran upheld a Department of the Army ruling that the Indians could not conduct memorial services today in Arlington National Cemetery.  The Indians vowed to defy the order.</p>

<p>At 6 p.m. yesterday, the Indians, who had loosened their grip on the building earlier in the day and removed barricades erected Thursday night, again blocked off all entrances and ordered all security guards out.</p>

<p>The mood last night contrasted sharply with the relaxed atmosphere earlier in the day, when the Indians had prepared to abandon the building and move to the General Services Administration's Departmental Auditorium blocks away.</p>

<p>The GSA had offered the use of the auditorium day and night, but when the first Indians arrived at the building at Constitution Avenue and 13th Street, they found the doors locked.</p>

<p>Charging that they had been "ambushed," the Indian leaders rejoined some 300 others who had remained at the BIA building cleaning up and removing barricades, and announced they would remain there indefinitely.</p>

<p>A GSA spokesman said the auditorium had remained locked up because its use had been offered contingent on the "peaceful and complete" evacuation of the BIA building.</p>

<p>Indian spokesmen denied ever making such an agreement, and charged that the GSA was "plotting" to lock them out of both buildings.</p>

<p>"I smell a rat," said Russell Means, a coordinator of the "Trail of Broken Treaties" caravan that began arriving in Washington Monday for a week of "peaceful" demonstrations to dramatize the needs of Indian people.</p>

<p>"They want assurance that we won't occupy both places, but we want assurances that we won't be left out," he said.</p>

<p>The Indians milled around the BIA building most of the day yesterday while their leaders negotiated with Bruce--who later endorsed some of their demands--and sought help from area groups and citizens.</p>

<p>As word of the court restraining order spread, they again locked all doors and instituted an elaborate security system that included ordering all women to the building's upper floors.</p>

<p>By 7 p.m. yesterday, most telephones in the building, except for a handful of pay phones, were cut off.</p>

<p>Indian leaders insisted they would not leave the BIA building until their demands were met.  They included:</p>

<p>- That the White House make a "firm commitment" to back 20 proposals ranging from the abolition of the BIA to stricter adherence to existing treaties.</p>

<p>- The firing of Assistant Secretary of Interior Harrison Loesch; Deputy BIA Commissioner John Crow and National Council on Indian Opportunity Director Robert Robertson.</p>

<p>- Return of "all bones and artifacts of our ancestors" to Indian people for reburial.</p>

<p>- Inclusion of "urban and landless Indians" in services provided for treaty Indians.</p>

<p>About 300 Indians remained in the building overnight, most of them sleeping wrapped in blankets and sleeping bags in upper floors, hallways and offices.  A few stood guard at windows and entrances.</p>

<p>BIA commissioner Bruce was one of a handful who reported to work yesterday morning.  Most employees were told by their superiors to take the day off.</p>

<p>The building manager Conrad E. Broadt, said a "conservative estimate" of the damage made to equipment and furniture during the takeover was $250,000.</p>

<p>At a morning press conference, "Trail" spokesman Russell Means, said his group was "not satisified" with a tentative agreement reached with White House and Department of Interior officials late Thursday.</p>

<p>White House Representative Brad Peterson had agreed to interview the group's 20-point demands and reply in writing "within 45 to 60 days," Means said.</p>

<p>"I'm not satisfied, but the doors are opening that heretofore were closed to us, and that's the best we can expect from the U.S. government," he said.</p>

<p>But, when a group of Indians reached the Departmental Auditorium, which Means and other group leaders had said would be open for the remainder of their stay, they found the building's doors locked.</p>

<p>The Indians reconvened at the BIA building, which by noon had been nearly vacated, and began a series of meetings with Bruce and other BIA officials.</p>

<p>By midafternoon, Bruce had agreed to back most of the Indian demands, and the Indian leaders said they would remain in the BIA building until the demands were met.</p>

<p>"This is not a blockade, it is not an occupation," declared Verlon Bellecourt, National Director of the American Indian Movement and one of the "Trails" coordinators.</p>

<p>He said his group would "try to let the BIA function in as near to normalcy as possible when they come back Monday."</p>

<p>In an emotional afternoon meeting for some 400 Indians in the building, Bruce made his first appearance since the demonstrators began arriving in town Monday.  His pledge for support of the Indian pledges was warmly received by the crowd.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="pA10"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Washington Post</hi>, November 5, 1972, p. A10.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Another 'Wounded Knee' Was Feared Friday Night</head>

	<p>Friday night, most of the more than 500 American Indians inside the Bureau of Indian Affairs building armed themselves with clubs, knives and a few bows and arrows and put on (lipstick) war paint for what they predicted might be "another Wounded Knee"--the famous 1890 battle in which an Army regiment massacred 250 to 300 Sioux Indians, most of them women and children.</p>
	
	<p>It was the second night in a row that Indians who have come here from across the land to petition the government to honor ancient treaties and improve their long-impoverished lot had prepared to fight.</p>
	
	<p>"We now call this the Native American Embassy . . . It is ours.  It belongs to the original, sovereign people of this land," Russell Means, a Sioux and a leader of the "Trail of Broken Treaties" caravan, told a U.S. marshal who came to serve him with eviction papers.</p>
	
	<p>Expecting an assault by U.S. marshals and police Friday night, to force them out of the building, the Indians barricaded the building for the second successive night.  Huge piles of desks, chairs and copying machines were stacked against all entrances; electric typewriters and anything on wheels were placed at every level of the central staircase to throw at advancing police--who never came.</p>
	
	<p>The Indians occupied the monolithic four-story marble building early Thursday.  They evicted Federal Protective Service guards at about 5 p.m. when most BIA employees had left for the day, put up barricades at the doors and hung American flags from the building's windows.</p>
	
	<p>A misunderstanding with guards at once exit ended with a scuffle in which several Indians were clubbed and two arrested.  Those clubbed ran through the building, their faces streaming blood from scalp wounds, calling to other Indians to arm themselves and defend the building against a police "attack."</p>
	
	<p>The sight of blood and news of the brief violence frightened and angered Indians who earlier had told a press conference they had come "in peace" for a week of peaceful protests.  The history of the white man's injustice to Indians, and this fresh though minor bloodletting appeared to strengthen their determination to hold the building.</p>
	
	<p>"We will not leave.  We will fight . . . we will die here if we have to," Dennis Banks, a national director of the organized American Indian Movement and a coordinator of the caravan, exhorted other Indians in the halls of the building Friday night.</p>
	
	<p>About 100 young children and the elderly, who had been removed to the fourth floor, were evacuated--taken to the YMCA for the night.  <!--dash in original copy-->Teen-agers carrying molotov cocktails, trash cans of hot water and one 50 pound carved pumpkin sat at upper windows ready to drop them on anyone attempting to enter the building.</p>
	
	<p>While tribal drums reverberated through the long halls of the building, the Indians prepared again to battle the white man.  There was so much joking but also anger and disbelief that this could be happening.  It seemed out of the story books.  There was much talk of Chief Sitting Bull, Crazy Horse, Chief Big Foot and Wounded Knee.</p>
	
	<p>"What did you use?" one youth asked as he admired the red stripes on his friend's face.</p>
	
	<p>"Lipstick.  I forgot to bring my paint."</p>
	
	<p>Many young men stripped to the waist and painted their chests, bedecked themselves in armbands and necklaces.  A few even had leather leggings and moccasins.  The older men wore fewer markings, whooped less, but also carried pieces of pipes and broken chair legs.</p>
	
	<p>A girl who had taped a letter-opening to the end of a broom handle to make a lethal-looking spear was told "You don't want to do that," by a sombre-faced Indian boy.</p>
	
	<p>"I guess not," she said, and untaped the letter opener.</p>
	
	<p>The threat of violence appeared real not only to the Indians but to some Bureau of Indian Affairs' officials, including Commissioner Louis R. Bruce, of Mohawk descent, who spent until about 4 a.m. yesterday inside the building, hoping his presence would help prevent a government assault.</p>
	
	<p>"I feel a responsibility to be here . . . in the hope it will be a peaceful affair," he told a group of English journalists who spent much of the night inside the barricaded building.</p>
	
	<p>LaDonna Harris, a Comanche, president of the Americans for Indian Opportunity and the wife of Sen. Fred. R. Harris (D-Okla.), also spent the night inside "because the commissioner is here and I hoped I could help."  In addition, Marion Barry, D.C. school board president, Charles Cassell, D.C. delegate candidates, and others joined the Indians inside.</p>
	
	<p>But, as it had Friday morning, dawn came yesterday with no attack from the white man.</p>
	
	<p>One exhausted Indian leader sighed about 4 a.m. Saturday and said, "I hope we can now get on with the reasons for being here."</p>
	
</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="pA1"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Washington Post</hi>, November 5, 1972, p. A1.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Officials, Indians Parley on Protest</head>

	<p>Protesting American Indians continued a third day of occupation of the Bureau of Indian Affairs building last night as negotiations with federal officials were adjourned after four hours.</p>

	<p>Leaders of the protests have been ignoring a federal court order to vacate the building.  Negotiations went forward yesterday after U.S. District Court Judge John H. Pratt refused to begin formal contempt proceedings.</p>
	
	<p>Talks are scheduled to resume at 9 a.m. today.  After hearing from negotiators this morning, Judge Pratt is expected to decide again whether to start a contempt action, which could lead to forcible eviction of the Indians.  It appears unlikely that a contempt hearing could begin before Monday.</p>

	<p>Little substantive progress was reported at yesterday's talks.  An Interior Department spokesman said no conclusions were reached.  Indian spokesmen said that they turned down government offers of alternative accomodations.  However, Russell Means, a protest coordinator, said, "We feel we are accomplishing something."</p>

	<p>The negotiating session, which began at 4:10 p.m., climaxed a day of tension and pagentry in and around the bureau's building at 19th Street and Constitution Avenue NW.</p>

	<p>Among the disparate groups that offered support to the estimated 500 Indians were those headed by black militant Stokely Carmichael and right-wing preacher Carl McIntire.</p>

	<p>In a related development, a three-judge panel of the U.S. Court of Appeals heard arguments calling for lifting of a lower court order banning a planned memorial service at the graves of two Indian war dead buried at Arlington National Cemetery.</p>

	<p>A decision in the case is scheduled for 4 p.m. today.</p>

	<p>Tentative plans had called for a memorial service at dawn today at the graves of Pfc. Ira Hayes and Sgt. John Rice.  Hayes, an Indian, was one of the marines who participated in the celebrated flag-raising at Iwo Jima in World War II.</p>

	<p>Vernon Bellecourt, a director of the American Indian <!-- continues on p. A10, Col. 4 --> Movement (AIM), one of the sponsoring organizations, said, "We will exhaust all our efforts in the legal system and then we're going to have that ceremony, regardless of the legal outcome."</p>

	<p>There was no contact yesterday between the protesters and the police, although several incidents led to tense situations.</p>

	<p>The Indians came here early last week in a caravan they called the "Trail of Broken Treaties."  They seek responses to nine demands, which include calls for the firing of several officials of the Bureau of Indian Affairs, strict adherence to existing treaties, and abolition of the bureau.</p>

	<p>Originally scheduled to begin Nov. 2 and last for a week, the Indian protest may now be extended until as late as Nov. 12 to make up for time lost in the dispute over occupation of the bureau, some protest leaders said yesterday.</p>

	<p>Yesterday's meeting between the protest leaders and federal officials took place at the General Services Administration Building at 18th and G Streets NW, a few blocks from the Bureau of Indian Affairs building.</p>

	<p>A main subject for discussion was housing for the protestors -- outside the bureau building.  Indian spokesmen said they rejected offers of accomodations at Bolling and Andrews Air Force Bases.  Government officials said the Indians have also repeatedly rejected an offer to use the Departmental Auditorium, on Constitution Avenue between 12th and 14th Streets NW, where 350 cots have been set up.</p>

	<p>Interior Department spokesmen said the original five-man government negotiating team was headed by Hans Walker, a Mandan Indian, who is head of the Department's Indian Water Rights Office.  (The Bureau of Indian Affairs is part of the Interior Department.)</p>

	<p>One official who was not a member of the original team, but who arrived at the Indians' request two hours after the start of the talks, was Louis R. Bruce, commissioner of the Bureau of Indian Affairs.</p>

	<p>Bruce is one of the bureau officials supported by the protesters.  He had met with their leaders for more than four hours through Friday night and Saturday morning in the bureau's building.</p>

	<p>But Bruce did not return to the building yesterday, and Russell Means, one of the coordinators of the protest, complained that Secretary of the Interior Rogers C. B. Morton personally had ordered Bruce to stay away.</p>

	<p>"Because Bruce made his stand with us last night, Morton ordered him to stay away.  Secretary Morton is inflating the situation and risking human lives," Means said.</p>

	<p><sic>"</sic>Robert A. Kelley, director of communication for Interior, said, "It was suggested to the commissioner that he not remain in the building.  It was felt by the leadership here--the Secretary was involved--that no one should be over there while we are in negotiations ordered by the court."</p>

	<p>The occupation of the building, which began at dusk Thursday, attracted a large crowd of curious yesterday, with traffic jams on Constitution Avenue and tourists and police viewing the activities from the sidewalk and across the street on the Mall.</p>

	<p>It was a scene worth seeing.  A tepee, about 20 feet tall, stands on the main lawn, near the flagpole where the American flag flew upside down, at half-staff.</p>

	<p>A cordon of Indians, brandishing a variety of homemade weapons, held back the public, and at times the press, with the aid of long poles that they stretched across the sidewalk.</p>

	<p>Indians--men, women, and children--hung from windows of the three-story building; others were on the roof, holding tiles that had been removed from the top of the building, and displaying buckets that apparently were filled with water.</p>

	<p>The tension apparently was too much for one man who had been in the building for several days.  Companions said he began to feel that he was being blamed for the destruction of property inside, and thought fellow Indians were holding him captive.</p>

	<p>He abducted a young girl, perhaps 10 or 11, and holding a pair of scissors to her neck, walked her to the front entrance, demanding to "talk to a cop."</p>

	<p>John Trudell, a Sioux from Pawnee, Okla., wearing an Oklahoma University football jersey, said he crossed Constitution Avenue and relayed the request to a motorcycle policeman.</p>

	<p>"The cop told me, 'If you want to solve that problem, get a tomahawk.'"</p>

	<p>(Attempts to locate the policeman were unsuccessful, but another policeman confirmed the request for assistance was denied.)</p>

	<p>When the young Indian was told police would not come to him, he came out the main entrance, holding the girl as a shield.  But he was struck over the head by a club wielded by another Indian who had hidden in the adjourning doorway.</p>

	<p>Several Indians pummeled the man to the ground and struck him repeatedly.  A few minutes later, he was released, whereupon he ran, shoeless, along the mall toward the Washington Monument.</p>

	<p>Trudell said, "He needs medical care, and we're not psychiatrists."  He said he decision to free him was made by "his own people."  Trudell said both the young man and the girl were members of the Tuscarawas group from North Carolina.</p>

	<p>Several other protesters were given various kinds of medical assistance by a volunteer group that had set up a first aid station in one of the BIA offices.</p>

	<p>The incident with the scissors occurred shortly after Carmichael had left the building.  Carmichael, saying he was speaking as head of the All-African People's Revolutionary Party, offered to "support this movement 100 per cent.</p>

	<p>The question of native Americans is not just a question of civil rights," he said.  "This land is their land . . . we have agreed to do whatever we can to provide help . . . there can be no settlemen until their land is returned to them."</p>

	<p>Mr. McIntire led about 200 of his supporters to the BIA after a rally at the U.S. Capitol in support of South Vietnam President Thieu.</p>

	<p>He called out qualified support of the Indian cause: "All right you Indians, we're here to give you some greetings.  We're all good Americans and I want you to have your rights."  But he warned them not to follow "those inside your group who seek to align Indians with the Communists."</p>

	<p>Dennis Banks one of the Indians' spiritual leaders, told McIntire, "I'm going to accept our support, but you don't have our support."</p>

	<p>Then someone told McIntire that if he really wanted to help someone, he should march on the Interior Department and order Secretary Morton to free Commissioner Bruce.</p>

	<p>McIntire set off on the two-block march, but got his marching orders confused and led his little band of followers in chanting "Free Morton, Free Morton."</p>

	<p>Inside the BIA, Indians complained to Clayton Williams, a Justice Department community relations consultant, that BIA estimates of $250,000 damage to the building were grossly exaggerated.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="pA1"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Washington Post</hi>, November 7, 1972, p. A6.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Legacy of Suspicion Changes Protest Into Confrontation</head>

<p>"We come in peace," the Indian leaders of the "Trail of Broken Treaties" caravan said last week as they arrived in Washington for a round of issue workshops, spiritual services and meetings with government officials.</p>

<p>Instead, there is the spectacle of those same Indian leaders and their hundreds of followers in armed occupation of the Bureau of Indian Affairs building.  Peace has turned into confrontation.</p>

<p>The issues have become clouded in angry rhetoric, court battles have replaced the spiritual services and the promised meetings with government officials have turned into angry haggling over details of food and lodging.</p>

<p>The explanation for this unhappy turnabout is as simple perhaps as midunderstood instructions from one security guard to another and as complicated as the hundreds of years of tragic conflict between the Indians and the white men who came to challenge them.</p>

<p>When the Indians occuped the Indian Affairs building Thursday morning, it seemed clear to observers then that their intention was to remain there only long enough for more adequate accomodations to be arranged.  The mood was still hopeful, the leadership still intent on reasoned discourse.</p>

<p>After a day of negotiations with BIA officials, a tentative agreement on housing was reached.  But even as it was being announced, a fight broke out between a small number of youthful demonstrators and a new shift of guards apparently not yet informed that the Indians were being permitted to stay.</p>

<p>It was then that the barricades first went up.  In the confusion the agreement was abandoned and has not been replaced.  With limited hindsight, that fight seems the simplest explanation for the confrontation.</p>

<p>But the petty dispute, at the same time, was a legacy of the suspicion and frustration that the Indians brought with them to Washington, born from long experience of dealing with the bureaucracy and the bitterness over the suffering and deprivation they claim has long been forced upon them.</p>

<p>Ironically, the portent for the "Trail of Broken Treaties" was good.  The Nixon administration has pledged to meet long-standing Indian demands for greater self-management without loss of badly needed federal support.</p>

<p>In a major address on July 8, 1970, President Nixon said:</p>

<p>"It is long past the time that the Indian policies of the federal government began to recognize and build upon the capacities and insights of the Indian people . . . The time has come to break decisively with the past and to create conditions for a new era in which the INdian future is determined by Indian acts and Indian decisions."</p>

<p>The President proposed a number of measures to protect Indian land and water rights, to expand Indian economic opportunities and improve education and health services.  The package was a complex one, given to political considerations on Capital Hill and bickering among the Indians themselves over what they wanted.</p>

<p>Thus far, the bulk of the administration bills and modifications put forward by congressional committees still remain to be enacted.</p>

<p>Nonetheless, many observers have recorded a greater sense of concern for Indian rights at the highest levels of government and a new spirit of activism among many of the bureaucrats charged with carrying out policy.  The BIA, once accused of mediocrity, has been praised lately by editorialists sympathetic to the Indians, for the energy and creativity of some of its officials.</p>

<p>Despite the surge of militant Indian activity in recent years (the 1969 seizure of Alcatraz Island off the California coast being the best known example) the prospect of an Indian caravan descending on Washington in the days just before the election was greeted with forebearance by the administration--at least publicly.</p>

<p>A letter dated Nov. 1 to "Trail leaders from Robert Robertson, executive director of the National Council on Indian Opportunity (a group in the Vice President's office), had this to say:</p>

<p>"All of us in the administration have enjoyed working with the co-chairmen of the Trail of Broken Treaties Caravan.  From the very first meeting with Mr. Bob Burnett and Mr. Ralph Ware on October 20, we have stressed our desire that the caravan visit result in an amicable, productive discussion of all the substantive issues you plant to present to us."</p>

<p>Later in the same letter, Robertson offered the use of two government auditoriums for planned activities.</p>

<p>The surface impression of goodwill, however, began to fade as soon as the Indians actually started to arrive.  Their scheduled ceremony at the Arlington gravesite was turned down by the Army.  Accomodations at local churches, supposedly arranged by caravan leaders in advance, turned out to be inadequate and the leaders blamed the government for the problem.</p>

<p>They said that officials had intervened to stop the churches from cooperating and the only one that provided facilities, St. Stephens' and the Incarnation at 16th and Newton Streets NW, "had rats bigger than cats running over our little children."</p>

<p>"We were forced into the BIA," Vernon Bellecourt, a "Trail" leader, said at a press conference.</p>

<p>The Indians produced a memorandum dated Oct. 11 from Harrison Loesch, assistant secretary for public land management within the Interior Department, to Louis R. Bruce, commissioner of the BIA: "subject--no direct or indirect assistance to American Indian Movement demonstration in Washington in early November."</p>

<p>Loesch's order to Bruce that "the bureau was not to provide any assistance" to the Indians seemed to go counter to the administration's public stance.  Interior yesterday confirmed the existence of such a memorandum but said it was later superseded.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="pA1"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Washington Post</hi>, November 7, 1972, p. A1.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Order Delayed, Indians Stay in Offices</head>

<p>Granted an 11th-hour reprieve by the U.S. Court of Appeals, several hundred heavily armed Indian protesters retained control of the Bureau of Indian Affairs building last night for the fifth consecutive day.</p>

<p>A three-judge panel of the appellate court delayed until 9 p.m. Wednesday an earlier lower court order that the Indians leave the occupied building by 6 p.m. or be forcibly removed by government authorities.</p>

<p>The Court of Appeals decision followed a series of threats by the members of the "Trail of Broken Treaties" caravan to burn the government building, located at Constitution Avenue and 19th Street, four blocks from the White House.</p>

<p>The Indians also vowed to fight to the death if police moved against them.  The Indians have retained control of the building since Thursday, when they came here from across the country to seek redress of what they consider wrongs visited on them by U.S. policies.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, negotiations continued early today in the Executive Office Building offices of Leonard Garment, special consultant to the President.  Among those taking part were Garment, Frank Carlucci, associate director of the Office of Management and Budget, and negotiators for the Indians.</p>

<p>Among other things, the negotiators were reported to be discussing the Indians' demand for the immediate firing of Assistant Interior Secretary Harrison Loesch, who supervises Indian affairs.</p>

<p>The Court of Appeals ruling, which superseded an earlier order by U.S. District Court Judge John H. Pratt, was handed down at 7:15 p.m., following a closed door hearing before Chief Judge David L. Bazelon and Judges Edward A. Tamm and Harold Levanthal.</p>

<p>While setting aside Judge Pratt's 6 p.m. deadline for evacuating the building, the Court of Appeals decision specifically provided U.S. marshals and other law enforcement authorities with "latitude as to how and when to carry out" the District Court ruling "subsequent to" 9 p.m. Wednesday.</p>

<p>The Court of Appeals ruling also declared that no contempt proceedings will be brought against any protesters who move from the BIA to the nearby Departmental Auditorium or otherwise "terminate their unlawful possession of the (BIA) building."</p>

<p>The three-judge panel said the postponment was designed to give the government time to arrange for "appropriate sanitary and commissary facilities" in the Departmental Auditorium.</p>

<p>Of the 9 p.m. Wednesday deadline, the Court of Appeals warned, "No extensions will be granted."</p>

<p>Immediately following the ruling, court sources said, U.S. Attorney Harold H. Titus Jr. took steps to advise law enforcement officials at the BIA building of the court's decision.</p>

<p>Emotions of the Indian protesters peaked about 3 p.m. when word of the court order reached the BIA from the U.S. District Court and a 100-man "security line" formed in front of the building.</p>

<p>Armed with clubs and makeshift spears--some with sharp knives lashed to the ends--the Indians vowed to fight to the death, if necessary, to retain control of the building.</p>

<p>"When and if the forces of U.S. government move in on the Indian people, we will fight to the death," said Russell Means, a leader of the "Trail of Broken Treaties" group.  "We've had more time to prepare our defenses.  When we go, the building goes," added Means.</p>

<p>Attorney Terrence Sidly of the American Indian Defense League, warned, "If they want this building burned and people killed, they (the police) should go in."</p>

<p>As a succession of Indians spoke in a similar vein over a loudspeaker, other protesters hurriedly prepared for the expected invasion by the authorities.</p>

<p>Two Indians carrying what appeared to be powerful bows and a number of arrows went to the roof of the four-story sandstone building, while others positioned themselves inside windows, holding firehoses.</p>

<p>Many of the windows facing Constitution Avenue were criss-crossed with adhesive tape, apparently to minimize splintering glass.  One protester, ignoring a series of speakers, smashed a half dozen tile drainage grates and collected the pieces.</p>

<p>One Indian protester observed by a reporter had a small-caliber revolver protruding from a pocket.  Others had table legs with sharp spikes imbedded in the ends.</p>

<p>Several lipsticks were passed along the heavily armed skirmish line, and the Indians painted warlike lines across their faces.</p>

<p>At the height of preparations, Dennis Banks, national field director for the American Indian Movement, faced a crowd of onlookers lined along Constitution Avenue and said, "I invite all of you to stay and witness the atrocities that are about to happen."</p>

<p>One Indian making defense preparations was Ralph Ware, chief negotiator in the unsuccessful talks with government officials.</p>

<p>A clinical psychologist from Minnesota, Ware held a makeshift club in his hand and said, "I am not really a fighter, but these are my people.  It's going to take a lot for me to swing this club . . . It took me a long time to decide this."</p>

<p>Ware, who said he once almost decided to stay inside the building with the women and children, was approached by his wife, a small, black-haired woman with tears in her eyes.  "I decided to stay," he said, and then embraced her.</p>

<p>About 4:30, Vernon Bellecourt, director of the American Indian Movement, emerged from the BIA and made an appeal for blacks to join in the defense of the building.  Recalling that blacks had been enlisted to fight Indians following their emancipation, Bellecourt said, "Dont' let the white man make you do it again."</p>

<p>Earlier in the day, the Washington chapter of the Black Panther Party had pledged its support of the Indian protest in a written statement.  However, there were few blacks in evidence outside the BIA.</p>

<p>The authority for the government to retake the BIA building by force was issued by Judge Pratt at 2:30 p.m., but its execution was suspended by the judge until 6 p.m. in order to permit attorneys for the Indians to appeal to the U.S. Court of Appeals.</p>

<p>In issuing his ruling, which was made at the behest of the Justice Department, Judge Pratt said the Indians "should be put on notice that the government is going to retake that building and the sooner that they (the Indians) comply with this order, the better off they are going to be."</p>

<p>Judge Pratt made his decision over the pleas of James Heller, an ACLU lawyer representing the "Trail of Broken Treaties" caravan who warned of "the dreadful possibility of bloodshed."</p>

<p>Judge Pratt issued an order last Friday directing the Indians to leave the BIA, but he put no time limit on that ruling because negotiations between the protesters and government officials were then still underway.</p>

<p>In yesterday's brief hearing in U.S. District Court, it was disclosed that Judge Pratt had conducted a hearing at his Chevy Chase home at 3 a.m. Saturday with attorneys for the Indians and representatives of the U.S. attorney's office.</p>

<p>The judge said that he had received assurances then by both sides that an agreement over such grievances as housing and transportation for the protesters could be reached peacefully and, as a result, he stayed the execution of Friday's order until yesterday.</p>

<p>"It seems to me that the representations made to me Saturday morning have not borne fruit, and that conditions are worse than they were," the judge said yesterday.</p>

<p>The order issued yesterday directed the U.S. marshals and "other such law enforcement officials as my be necessary" to arrest and bring before the court any Indians who "willfully and deliberately" violate the injunction so that they could show cause why they should not be held in criminal contempt.</p>

<p>Because of the District Court's order that they vacate the building, the Indians canceled plans for a noon march to Arlington Cemetery to hold religious ceremonies at the gravesites of Indian war dead.</p>

<p>Instead, the demonstrators hurriedly began fortifying the BIA against the anticipated assault by police.</p>

<p>The court ruling followed by two hours a reluctant denunciation of the BIA takeover by the National Tribal Chairmen's Association, a government-backed Indian organization that includes among its membership many older Indian tribal chiefs and officials of tribal councils.</p>

<p>In a press conference, several tribal leaders pledged support of some of the "good points" made by the protestors, but all the NTCA members present disassociated themselves from the seizure of the BIA building and condemned the threat of the use of force to retain control.</p>

<p>Near the end of the press conference, about a dozen younger Indians burst into the Roger Smith Hotel conference room and accused the NTCA elders of not representing the majority of American Indians.  The protesters accused the tribal chiefs of being BIA-funded spokesmen for larger reservations that "can fly people across the country to meeting in hotels here."</p>

<p>Robert Lewis, governor of the Zuni (New Mexico) tribal council, said the NCTA was concerned that continued occupation of the BIA building would result in injuries to Indians.</p>

<p>"We are a long way from home.  The culture of our people is involved.  We had cultures and civil rights before the settlers landed, and what little we have left we want to preserve," Lewis said.</p>

<p>Sitting impassively in the crowded and brightly lighted conference room, Lewis ignored the protesters' jeering and added, "We have no hatred in our hearts for these people (the protesters).  That is not our way."</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="pB1"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Washington Post</hi>, November 8, 1972, p. B1.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Indians Seize Files as Some Go Home</head>

<p>Spokesmen for American Indians occupying the Bureau of Indian Affairs said yesterday that they have read and removed from the building boxes of files that they say show "scandalous if not criminal" exploitation of Indians by senators, congressmen, BIA officials and corporate interests.</p>

<p>Russell Means, a leader of the Trail of Broken Treaties caravan, told reporters on the BIA steps that the documents include personnel and real estate records and FBI investigative reports.</p>

<p>He did not go into detail, but said the documents show "collusion, at least, in ripping off Indian land, water, fishing, agriculture and mineral rights."</p>

<p>With the seizure of the files, carried out inconspicuously in jackets, boxes and blankets, Means said, "For all intents and purposes, the BIA is abolished."</p>

<p>In a statement Monday, Interior Secretary Rogers C. B. Morton said, "Vital land, water and personnel records have been destroyed.  These will take months to reassemble, if that is at all possible."</p>

<p>The claim that the documents had been taken came during a day that saw negotiations continue between Indians and administration officials, and the departure of many other Indians for their homes.  This was in line with the original timetable, which called for a week of demonstrations to end yesterday, but well before a court-ordered eviction set for tonight at 9.</p>

<p>The possibility of a violent confrontation between large numbers of Indians and federal mershals subsided somewhat, as Means said, "Many have left because of jobs, family commitments.  As the leadership has come to recognize, these people have to get home.  That's the next set of problems."</p>

<p>He vowed, however, that at least some Indians would remain behind to confront any federal force seeking to evict them.  This would demonstrate, he said, that officials waited only for the election to carry out the eviction.  "Also, many of us are ready to die for our beliefs."</p>

<p>At noon yesterday, an Indian spokesman estimated that there were about 800 Indians in the building; by yesterday evening their numbers had dwindled as some were seen leaving, taking bedrolls with them.  No precise figures were availabe.</p>

<p>The Indian negotiators, about a dozen, mostly middle-aged men, left for a White House meeting around noon.  They were led by Hank Adams, Indian legal adviser, who said the primary item on the agenda was "to negotiate an agreement for our departure from this building."</p>

<p>Late yesterday, the Indian representatives agreed to continue talks with a special task force that is to be made up of officers of all the federal agencies operating programs for Indians.  The task force is to be led by Leonard Garment, special consultant to the President, and Frank Carlucci, deputy director of the Office of Management and Budget.</p>

<p>An Interior Department spokesman said last night that the task force would review federal Indian policy and Indian needs.  The body, which will exist for six months, will submit recommendations to the Presidenty by June 1, 1973, together "with any additional or independent views of the Indian representatives," the spokesman said.</p>

<p>Vernon Bellecourt, a spokesman for the American Indian Movement, said last night that despite the agreement to continue talks with the new task force, the Indians would not leave the BIA until the government acts on the issues that brought the Indians to Washington.</p>

<p>These include demands that treaties be respected, the BIA be abolished, several federal officials be fired, and, in an apparent contradiction, that $50 million be restored to the BIA budget.</p>

<p>In their sixth day of th occupying the BIA building at 19th Street and Constitution Avenue NW, Indian leaders stressed that the seizure was incidental to the purpose of the caravan.</p>

<p>"We did not come here as a military force to occupy any building whatsoever," Means said.  "If we've had problems in security, among ourselves, it is because we're not a discplined military unit."</p>

<p>Security was tight through the day.  Reporters were not allowed inside the building, as they had been days earlier.  Around 9 a.m., wire cables were strung from first floor windows almost to Constitution Avenue, thus roping off much of the BIA front lawn from sympathizers, spectators and newsmen.</p>

<p>Later, around 4:30 p.m., some Indians emerged from the building saying they had captured a "white cop."  They said they found him inside the building, complete with gun, handcuffs and police identification.</p>

<p>The man came outside and identified himself as metropolitan Officer Roger O'Day.  He said he had walked into the rear of the building.  "I was on assignment in the area," he said.  "I was not ordered to go inside.  I was just curious."</p>

<p>For the most part, however, the once tense mood at the BIA seemed to lessen as the morning chill and gray sky were replaced by an unusually warm November day and blue skies.  Occasionally, bits of humor crept in.</p>

<p>An Indian woman, strolling down the steps, remarked, "I never saw so many cameras in my life."  At least some of the cameras belonged to Indians.</p>

<p>Seventh graders from the Field School, 1711 Connecticut Ave. NW, visited the scene as part of a class project on Indians.  Eric Jackson, 12, wanted to know about Indian reservations.</p>

<p>"Is it as bad as the ghetto?" he asked.  A Cheyenne replied, "It's just as bad."</p>

<p>Then the Indian added, "You should live out in the country.  There is fresh air.  You grab your gun and go into your backyard and go hunting . . . rabbits, bear, prairie chickens.  In the afternoon, you can go fishing."</p>

<p>Throughout the day, families, many from the suburbs, dropped off food at the BIA for the Indians.  Johanna Gordon, of Lorton, Va., came with her two sons, daughter-in-law and granddaughter to deliver canned meat and vegetables.</p>

<p>"I think these people have really a gripe," she said.  "Some people should help them."</p>

<p>Another woman walked up to an Indian security guard, a 25-year-old Mohawk from Cleveland, and handed him a $5 bill.  "I don't handle the money," he said.  "I trust you to put it in the pot," she said, and he thanked her.</p>

<p>Breakfast yesterday was eggs and coffee, the Mohawk said.  It was cooked and served in the BIA basement cafeteria, he said, with about 20 people preparing the food.</p>

<p>Most of the Indians slept inside the building, on concrete floors, in chairs, on rugs.  The YMCA, at 18th and G Streets NW, housed and fed about 150 women and children, many of whom returned to the BIA during the daytime.</p>

<p>Aside from the logistics of their stay, some Indians expressed frustration with what they said was the public's failure to understand their plight.</p>

<p>"A lot of people come up and don't know what we're doing here," said a Cheyenne from Montana, who appeared to be in his 30s.</p>

<p>He stood on the steps close by a small sign that read, "Closed for Repairs."  "One woman came up and said, 'Why is this building closed for repairs?  Seven days here and they come up with a stupid question like that."</p>

<p>Differences between the Indians at the BIA and their tribal leaders also emerged from conversations.  "We can't get anything through our tribal leaders because they get BIA money," said a middle-aged Sioux woman from Pine Ridge, S.D.  "We're grassroots.  We're the poorest of the poor."</p>

<p>The Cheyenne from Montana said, "This movement here had to do something to get our point across because the tribal chieftains ain't going to do this."</p>

<p>As if to confirm the split, Earl Old Person, of Browning, Mont., chairman of the Blackfeet Tribal Council, denounced the demonstrators.  He said yesterday, "We have elected tribal leaders.  These demonstrators do not represent grassroots Indians."</p>

<p>Meanwhile, Peter MacDonald, Navaho tribal chieftain, sent a telegram to President Nixon urging that a 10-member commission be created, composed of Indians and government officials, to arbitrate the issues.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, the occupying Indians received support elsewhere from 100 Indians and their supporters who seized BIA offices in Seattle, Wash.  They vowed to remain there until demands of demonstrators here are met.</p>

<p>Rep. Shirley Chisholm (D-N.Y.) pledged her "full support" to the Trail of Broken Treaties caravan in a telegram yesterday.  Dr. Benjamin Spock, People's Party presidential candidate, appeared in person yesterdy afternoon to offer his support.</p>

<p>Spock ignored the advise of his Secret Service guards, and entered the BIA accompanied by Indian leader Bellecourt.  The two emerged minutes later, at which time Spock praised the Indians and their cause.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="pC1"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Washington Post</hi>, November 9, 1972, p. C1.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Protest by Indians Sought an End to Paternalism</head>

<p>The Indians who came to Washington on the "Trail of Broken Treaties" carried a plan to completely redesign the relationship of their people to the federal government that for so long has made decisions for them.</p>

<p>The issues raised in the plan have been obscured by the seizing of the Bureau of Indian Affairs building, but the underlying causes of Indian discontent will remain no matter how that eye-catching turmoil is resolved.</p>

<p>The over-riding issue, according to specialists here in Indian problems, is the growing Indian demand for self-determination: an end to what amounted in the past to alternating paternalism and neglect by the federal government.</p>

<p>The essence, said George Mitchell, one of the founders of the activist American Indian Movement, "is that Indian people should control their own lives."</p>

<p>Mitchell's general observation covers a spectrum of Indian opinion that seems to range from outright separatism to the more prevailing view that Indians are entitled to a greater voice in directing the many educational, welfare and public works projects that serve them.</p>

<p>There appears to be a firm agreement, however, that all Indians are seeking a guarantee that their lands will not be taken from them.  Even the separatists favor massive federal funding to assure the preservation of traditional Indian culture and the opportunity for badly needed social and economic advancement.</p>

<p>In an eight-page single spaced document that forms the "Trail of Broken Treaties" demands, 20 separate propositions are put forward, all covering the same basic theme of enhanced Indian reponsibility.</p>

<p>The proposals, approved at the AIM convention in St. Paul two weeks ago, cover a multitude of complex questions and Indian experts disagree among themselves on exactly how they are to be interpreted.</p>

<p>For example, there is a provision calling for renewed Indian treaty-making authority, a right that was withdrawn by Congress in 1871 when it assumed a kind of colonialist supervision over Indian matters.</p>

<p>In the 19th century, the treaties amounted to agreements between sovereign Indian nations and the Washington authorities.  The militants seem bent on establishing that kind of relationship again.  For the most part, however, the Indians appear to favor treaties as contracts.</p>

<p>This concept of "contracting"--giving the Indians authority to direct their own educational, welfare and health programs with funds from Washington--has been gaining support in recent years as a viable method of increasing Indian pride in themselves.</p>

<p>As embodied in the Indian plan, contracting is certainly not a radical departure.  President Nixon himself accepted the motion in a major address on Indian affairs in July 1970.</p>

<p>The goal of any new national policy toward the Indian people, he said, should be "to strengthen the Indian's sense of autonomy without threatening his sense of community."</p>

<p>"We must assure the Indian that he can assume control of his own life without being separated involuntarily from the tribal group.  And we must make it clear that Indians can become independent of federal control without being cut off from federal concern and federal support."</p>

<p>The principles enunciated by the President and those put forward by the young militants occupying Bureau of Indian Affairs are not so very far apart in the view of specialists here.</p>

<p>Basically, the Indians wish to move in the same directions as the White House, only faster and perhaps further.  It is not unlike the situation that prevailed in the mid-1960s when blacks in America found rhetorical agreement with President Johnson but disagreed on the pace of change.</p>

<p>Continuing the black analogy, Indian specialists here say the AIM is similar to the Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee and the Black Power advocates who espoused a kind of nationalism that at times bordered on outright separatism.</p>

<p>Moreover, much of the AIM leadership--which largely overlaps with that of the "Trail of Broken Treaties"--comes from urban Indians, rather than those remaining on the reservations.</p>

<p>The urban Indians, who now represent about half of the 800,000 Indians in the country, tend to produce a more militant leadership, experts maintain than the reservations, where tribal officials are selected along more traditional lines.</p>

<p>George Mitchell, himself a resident now of Washington, said that he retains his ties to the Chippewa reservation in Minnesota where he once lived.  It's not a matter of where you live, he said, but of common Indian problems.</p>

<p>The "grass roots" people who joined the occupation of the Bureau of Indian Affairs building came from tribes throughout the country.  Some traveled from reservations, some came from city centers.</p>

<p>"They are all Indians," said Mitchell "and these are their proposals."</p>

<p>Besides the question of restoring Indian lands (the plan calls for a 110 million acre "native land base" by 1976) and an overhaul of all existing treaty-contracts the "Trail" proposal seeks a new federal agency to replace the existing BIA.</p>

<p>This "Office of Federal Indian Relations and Community Reconstruction" would recognize Indian prerogatives to self-control, but at the same time would funnel billions of federal funds to what the proposal calls the "Indian Nations."</p>

<p>The main reason for wanting to abolish the BIA, in the view of Indian specialists, is that it represents the past approach to Indian needs: white managers, for the most part, supervising Indian schools, roads, real estate management, even police.</p>

<p>While the Indians reject that paternalism, they are equally opposed to the policy adopted in the Eisenhower years known as "termination," aimed at the closing of all reservations and severance of federal ties.</p>

<p>For the few tribes involved, "termination" was a disaster.  Without federal trust protection, their lands and resources were quickly taken over by shrewd business interests.  The prospect of forced assimilation created widespread concern about the preservation of Indian culture.</p>

<p>As a policy, "termination" has been abandoned for more than a decade, but its memory haunts the Indians anxious to reconcile their quest for dignity of independence with a continuing reliance on Washington's financial support.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="pC1"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Washington Post</hi>, November 9, 1972, p. C1.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">'The Government Forced Us to Action'</head>

<p>"We're having a fight to get our land back," said Kermit Fraser as he swung a club at a battered picture of the Old West.</p>

<p>Kermit is 9 years old.  A Santee Indian from Provo, Utah.</p>

<p>"Guess what I'm doing?" he said as he kicked away some debris that covered the floor of the Bureau of Indian Affairs building.  "I'm breaking out windows and knocking things."</p>

<p>Kermit was too late to do any real damage.</p>

<p>It had been done earlier, by older, angrier Indian protesters.</p>

<p>"The destruction you see here is the reflection of the pulse of our people," Vernon Bellecourt told a press conference earleir in the day.</p>

<p>The destruction of the contents appeared to be total.  Structural damage was minimal, however, to the three-story building at 19th Street and Constitution Avenue NW that withstood what Bellecourt called "a crucial seven days."</p>

<p>Bellecourt and other spokesman for the American Indian Movement, whose supporters had laid seige to the BIA structure, threw open the building for inspection at 4:30 p.m. yesterday.  What remained was a shell of the building.</p>

<p>"It (the damage) is the pulse of many years of suffering.  It is a reflection of the anger and frustration of a people abused.  It is the feeling of our people, who have come to recognize the crimes that the United States government, the Department of Interior, the Bureau of Indian Affairs, and the dominant ruling class have committed against the sovereign native people."</p>

<p>A press conference was held in the second-floor office of BIA Commissioner Louis R. Bruce.  His desk was strewn with torn letters, crackers, a half-eaten carrot and peanut butter.</p>

<p>The paneled walls were scratched, leather chairs torn, pictures cut from their frames, telephones pulled loose and, as throughout the building, the floor was not visible for papers and other material that littered it.</p>

<p>"I know you guys are going to have a field day on this," Russell Means, an Indian spokesman, told members of "the racist press."</p>

<p>Means placed blame for the damage on the federal government.  He said the destruction occurred after an order to vacate the building at 6 p.m. Monday was served on the occupants.  (The order later was stayed until 9 p.m. yesterday.)</p>

<p>"The psychology of the federal government forced us to this action," Means said.</p>

<p>"We did not come here for a military operation," Means said, "but the federal government threatened us on four occasions, and only on the fourth time, when the ultimatum came at 6 p.m. Monday, did we prepare the building as you now see it."</p>

<p>Prior to that, "the leadership asked everyone not to rip off or destroy the property," Means said.  He added, "We had gone through files and documents (before Monday), getting them on film, or making copies or making notes, but we cleaned up this building every night."</p>

<p>On Saturday, for example, the first-floor auditorium was swept, scrubbed and polished on two separate occasions preceding "general assembly" meetings, Means said.</p>

<p>Many windows were broken early, but early claims by BIA spokesman that damage amounted to $250,000 was called "a gross exaggeration" by Indians.</p>

<p>No one would have called that amount an exaggeration last night.</p>

<p>Wind gusting 35 to 40 miles an hour whipped through broken windows and flapping Venetian blinds, sending thousands of pieces of correspondence and other bureaucratic paperwork swirling throughout the building.</p>

<p>Graffiti scrawled on walls, doors and chalkboards was a history lesson in the rape of the West: Seneca, Arapaho, Tuscarawa Nation, St. Paul Sioux, Tewa Pueblo, Tama, Chocta, Ponca, Osage, Blackfeet.</p>

<p>Slogans too: Custer Died For Your Sins, Remember Wounded Knee, Red Power, Geronimo for President, Indians Are Chosen People, White Slavery Isn't Fun Anymore, We Are Now.</p>

<p>Is Room 209, a map of the United States "depicting Indian land areas" was altered to include all 50 states.  A message "to the President and his servant" on the board placed a curse on the government from people "fighting to survive in our own country."</p>

<p>The Rosebud Indian Movement's Department of War had been headquartered in Room 219.  Personal belongings and pictures of its former occupants were on the floor, along with a book on client-centered therapy.</p>

<p>A wall on the third floor offered the belief that "BIA Indians Are Sellouts."  Inside an office nearby, an empty bottle of blackberry wine shared the floor with a silver, artificial Christmas tree and an empty Santa stocking.</p>

<p>Chairs and desks were stacked against the two elevators in the third floor hallway, beneath a poem that said: We want to be Indians, We want to be Read, We want to be Free or We want to be Dead.</p>

<p>Missing from the slogans were the usual vulgarisms of protest.  The closest thing to the common protest rhetoric was contained in an inscription on a drawing of an Indian-head nickel:  "This is just about the only Indian you give a damn about."</p>

<p>A sign over the entrance of the auditorium offered this explanation for the havoc:</p>

<p>"Gentlemen: I do not apologize for the ruin nor the so-called destruction of this mausoleum.  For in building anew, one must first destroy the old.  This is the beginning of a new era of rthe North American native people.  When history recalls our efforts here, our descendants will stand with pride, knowing their people were the only ones responsible for the stand taken against tyranny, injustice and the gross inefficiency of this branch of a corrupt and decadent government."</p>

<p>It was signed: The Native American Embassy.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="pA1"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Washington Post</hi>, November 11, 1972, p. A1.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">News Conference Confrontation</head>
<head type="sub">Indians Clash Over Money</head>

<p>Representatives of two Indian organizations charged one another yesterday with misusing federal money as the debate among Indians themselves continued in the aftermath of the sacking of the Bureau of Indian Affairs building.</p>

<p>The accusations were made during an angry confrontation that disrupted a press conference called by the National Tribal Chairmen's Association (NTCA).</p>

<p>Members of the NTCA, composed of older, more conservative leaders of reservation Indians, were accused of being brought to Washington by the Nixon administration to condemn the dissident American Indian Movement (AIM).</p>

<p>"Who paid your way here?" demanded Herbert Powless, Milwaukee coordinator of AIM.  "You are using government funds.  You got $50,000 from the Nixon administration for your convention last year."</p>

<p>(A White House source said $50,000 "sounds about right" for the amount of support given to NTCA.)</p>

<p>Chief Bob Jim of the Yakima (Wash.) Indian Nation, a member of the NTCA's executive board, countered: "Tell us where the $66,000 came from."</p>

<p>He was referring to the money used to pay the return expenses of the more than 1,000 Indians who followed the Trail of Broken Treaties caravan to Washington last week.</p>

<p>The encounter, which came during a press conference at the National Press Club, capped a day of bickering and blame-placing for the destruction at the BIA.  In other developments:</p>

<p>- BIA Commissioner Louis R. Bruce indicated he had been muzzled by the White House, lending support to speculation that he may be fired.</p>

<p>- Terms of amnesty for the protesters remained in contention, with demonstration leaders insisting they had a promise that no one would be prosecuted for "anything short of death" and White House spokesman saying the agreement did not cover "the extraordinary damage" or theft of documents.</p>

<p>- A third Indian organization, which shuttled the transportation money from the government to the demonstrators, complained that efforts to keep the protest peaceful failed "largely due to the apathy of the government agencies involved."</p>

<p>As tempers flared at the press club confrontation, Webster Two Hawk, president of the NTCA, asked that police be called.  Order was restored without police assistance, however.</p>

<p>Another of the AIM leaders, Carter Camp, called out that "you are part of the establishment.  You flew here first class, wear $200 suits, live in $20,000 houses and don't give a damn who goes to jail."</p>

<p>The latter was a reference to the NTCA demand that the protesters be prosecuted "for the senseless acts" of destruction that caused damage to the BIA building now estimated at more than $2 million.</p>

<p>In contrast to the NTCA members, who wore business suits and had short hair, the AIM spokesmen were attired in colorful Indian garb; several wore their hair in braids.</p>

<p>The NTCA leaders denied that their expenses had been paid by the government, or that they had been called to Washington to defend the Nixon administration.</p>

<p>"Some of us were here already, to talk about budget affairs, and others were meeting about Indian health care problems," said Chairman Wendell Chino of Mescalero, N.M.</p>

<p>Chief Jim charged that some of the Indians who came here to protest peacefully were stranded at the YMCA despite the acceptance of $66,000 by demonstration leaders.</p>

<p>Hank Adams, who has been AIM's chief negotiator with the federal government, said a full accounting of the money will be made, and denied that anyone was stranded.</p>

<p>He said some Indians who remained an extra night at the Y were given shares Thursday of $7,000 that remained after Wednesday night's distribution of travel funds.  Only $300 remains undistributed, Adams said, "and I've got that in my pocket."</p>

<p>The accounting will be made at a public hearing that Adams said Sen. Edward M. Kennedy (D-Mass.) has promised to call within 60 days.</p>

<p>When someone again shouted the charge that the chairmen's expenses were being paid by the government, Chief Vernon Lane of Lumni, Wash., nearly in tears, yelled back: "I paid my own way.  We took up a collection on the reservation to get me here so I could try to get 250 acres of our land back because a Navy base was being evacuated."</p>

<p>Two Hawk repeated sentiments he first had expressed on Thursday during a tour of the BIA building, namely that the perpetrators of the damage should be prosecuted and federal officials who permitted the rebels to take over the building should be held accountable.</p>

<p>As the bickering continued, Chairman Nathan Little Soldier, from North Dakota, observed that "this is what the press and TV enjoys.  We should work together.  We will work together.  My door and my hand is open to anyone.  We should adjourn rather than make fools of ourselves."</p>

<p>The rhetoric slowly cooled, and after the session broke up, several of the participants shook hands and traded pledges of Indian solidarity.</p>

<p>Earlier in the day, also at the Press Club, the National Congress of American Indians issued a statement that criticized the government's handling of the protest.</p>

<p>Charles E. Trimble, executive director, said that while the NCAI "has never encouraged, condoned or participated in tactics of disruption or destruction in our quest for justice for Indian people," it also has been "ever aware that we tread common paths with the leaders of the organizations which comprised the Trail of Broken Treaties."</p>

<p>Trimble said that after study of the "deep implications" of the caravan's 20-point demands, his organization will "find itself in support of many of the issues."</p>

<p>Trimble charged that "in the most sinister atmosphere imaginable, the Bureau of Land Management, in conjunction with the Vice President's own National Council on Indian Opportunity, is working clandestinely to muster tribal leaders for the defense of the administration.  Their efforts are to place the blame on the commissioner of Indian affairs."</p>

<p>Trimble said it was his organization that was used to channel the money, through NCAI's OEO-funded economic development program, from the government to the protesters.</p>

<p>"After receiving assurance that these funds would not be made as a pay-off at the expense of any existing or future reservation program or urban Indian programs, NCAI agreed to serve as a conduit to channel the amount of $66,650 to representatives of the demonstration.  No NCAI funds were used," Trimble said.</p>

<p>He said the terms of the agreement, and the amount, were established in negotiations between the White House and the Trail of Broken Treaties.</p>

<p>Trimble's suggestion that BIA Commissioner Bruce would become a scapegoat in the incident is shared by others, including some BIA employees.</p>

<p>Bruce has been incommunicado since the building was evacuated Wednesday night.  Interior Department spokesmen said Thursday that he was sick.</p>

<p>Yesterday, an aide said Bruce had agreed to be interviewed by The Washington Post in Room 4216 of the Interior Department at 2 p.m. when a reporter and photographer arrived there, Bob Gajdyp, director of planning for the BIA, said the commissioner had called and issued this statement: "Any statement from the commissioner will be issued from the White House."</p>

<p>Informed of the statement, a White House spokesmen who has been dealing with the BIA's troubles gasped, "The White House?  That's incredible."</p>

<p>He then left the telephone for a moment and returned to add: "If any restrictions have been imposed upon the commissioner, they didn't come from the White House.  We wouldn't do that kind of thing.  The Interior Department is empowered to make those decisions."</p>

<p>Bruce's superior, Harrison Loesch, assistant secretary of the Interior for public land management said, "This department has not put the commissioner under any wraps that I know of, but I judge that he got his orders.  He was on the negotiating team."</p>

<p>Loesch, who was one of the chief targets of the protesters, added that "I won't have any thing substantive to say myself for a few days.  We consider it good not to stir the water."</p>

<p>The secretary on Thursday suggested that an amnesty agreement made by White House negotiations should be ignored.  He said that his boss, Secretary Rogers C. B. Morton, planned to ask Attorney General Richard Kleindienst to "seek full-scale prosecution."</p>

<p>The matter of amnesty was still in question yesterday.  AIM negotiator Adams said he had been assured by the White House "as recently as two hours ago" that allconditions of the amnesty agreement, written and oral, would be upheld.</p>

<p>A White House spokesman, however, repeated the belief that the agreement did not cover the "extraordinary" damage to the building or the theft of government documents.</p>

<p>Adams said he understands the agreement to cover "anything that happened between Thursday at 4:15 p.m. (Nov. 2, first day of the occupation of the BIA) through Wednesday at 10 p.m." when the building was vacated.</p>

<p>He said none of the documents that were taken from the building have been destroyed, and that he plans to meet Monday with White House representatives to begin negotiations for their return.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="pB1"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Washington Post</hi>, November 15, 1972, p. B1.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Stolen BIA Artifacts, Documents Recovered</head>

<p>Traffic accidents and speeding arrests in three Western towns have led to the recovery of what is believed to be stolen documents and artifacts from the looted Bureau of Indian Affairs building here, a BIA spokesman said yesterday.</p>

<p>The recoveries, which occured in Clinton and Anadarko, Okla., and Horton, Kan., came as leaders of the Indians who took over the BIA building prepared to discuss the thefts in public here today.</p>

<p>A spokesman for the Trail of Broken Treaties announced that "disposition of stolen materials" would be discussed at a press conference this morning.  The spokesman would not say if any of the documents and art objects would be displayed.</p>

<p>Hank Adams, who has been chief negotiator for the protesters in their dealings with the White House, reportedly will be the principle spokesman at the news conference.</p>

<p>The FBI, which is conducting the investigation of the thefts, said its agents questioned nine occupants of a van, which overturned on Sunday near Clinton.</p>

<p>The Clinton Daily News reported that after the four young injured Indians who were patients at the Clinton Indian Hospital were questioned by agents, they checked themselves out against the advice of the hospital administrator.</p>

<p>One young man left the hospital in a wheel chair.  When the hospital said it did not have any crutches, he was carried to a waiting car.</p>

<p>The FBI in Oklahoma City said several pieces of office equipment were recovered from the disabled van, but denied a report taht documents had been found.</p>

<p>Details of the incidents--an accident and a speeding arrest--in Anadarko and Horton were not known.</p>

<p>A BIA spokesman also said several anonymous callers yesterday asked how stolen items could be returned.  Callers are being told to contact the FBI, which picked up 31 paintings at the YMCA here yesterday.</p>

<p>Romano Bennett, a Puyallup Indian who is an American Indian Movement coordinator in the state of Washington, said that while she "understood" the concern about the theft of files and artifacts, it is "incredible that artifacts have a higher value than the controls on Indian lives and the lack of service given, based on dollars expended and services received."</p>

<p>She said the BIA's release of its daily payroll indicated that "put on two or three reservations, (the money) would result in some economic development" not provided by the BIA.</p>

<p>A second congressional investigation of the takeover was announced yesterday by Rep. James A Haley (D-Fla.).</p>

<p>Haley, chairman of the House Interior Committee's subcommittee on Indian affairs, set Dec. 4, 5, and 6 for government officials to testify before his panel.</p>

<p>The subcommittee will "consider the circumstances surrounding the illegal seizure and occupation of the BIA building.  The subcommittee expects to hear only governmental witnesses "at this time" Haley said, with the probe directed "primarily at the persons directly responsible for the decisions made."</p>

<p>Haley said Indian leaders will appear at a later date.</p>

<p>Earlier, Sen. Edward M. Kennedy (D-Mass.) had said he would call a hearing for all persons involved in the BIA takeover, probably in about 60 days, at the time a special governmental task force is due to issue its own report on the incident.</p>

<p>Cleanup of the building, at 19th Street and Constitution Avenue NW continued yesterday, but workers still were not permitted to untangle the records strewn about the basement and first and second floors.</p>

<p>Reopening of the building to the BIA's 400 some employees, originally set for Friday, has been set back to next Tuesday, and even that date is optimistic, according to one BIA employee.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="pA23"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Washington Post</hi>, November 18, 1972, p. A23.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Sioux Leader Outraged</head>

<p>The chairman of the Oglala Sioux Tribal Council says he was outraged at destruction during Indian occupations of the Bureau of Indian Affairs building in Washington and a museum in Nebraska this week.</p>

<p>Dick Wilson, who is also president of the Oglala Sioux, strongly criticized the American Indian Movement (AIM), which led both demonstrations and said he would not permit their representatives on the vast Pine Ridge Reservation.</p>

<p>Wilson said Russell Means, a national official of AIM, is seeking permission from the United Sioux Tribes of South Dakota to visit the reservation, to relate AIM's views on what happened during the occupation of the Bureau of Indian Affairs.</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="pC1"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Washington Post</hi>, November 22, 1972, p. C1.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">BIA's Loesch: A Bureaucrat Unafraid to Speak Out</head>

<p>Harrison Loesch is an unusual Washington bureaucrat who has not been afraid to speak out about judges, his own boss, Interior Secretary Rogers C. B. Morton, the Nixon administration generally (although Loesch is a presidential appointee) and, especially the nation's Indians.</p>

<p>His strong opinions about Indians and how the government should handle them have put Loesch on the spot because, as assistant secretary of Interior for pulbic land management, Loesch oversees the federal Bureau of Indian Affairs.</p>

<p>One of the demands made by the Indians who took over and occupied the BIA building for several days earlier this month was that Loesch be fired.  He was accused of being anti-Indian and more interested in land development projects than in improving the lives of Indians.  Even some of his associates in the government have suggested anonymously that Loesch's recent pro forma resignation, required of all presidential appointees, may be accepted.</p>

<p>Loesch himself dates his troubles to a public admission shortly after his appointment that he did not really know much about Indians and the issues they have raised.  He went on the Dick Cavett television show after Bob Burnett, a spokesman for the American Indian Movement (AIM), "had spent 30 minutes telling about what bastards all those bureaucrats were.</p>

<p>"I knew I was going to get killed," Loesch said.</p>

<p>And he was right.  One statement he made on the show "really haunts me," he said.  "I said I knew nothing about the Indian problem when I came to Washington.  Well, that was pretty much true, but in this pressure cooker situation, you learn fast.</p>

<p>"I don't apologize now (for his knowledge of Indian affairs).  I'm no scholar, but I've learned," Loesch said.</p>

<p>Before his appointment, his experience has been limited to that of a small town western lawyer "defending a few indigent Navajos or Utes who got drunk and disorderly while passing through town."</p>

<p>Hank Adams, principal negotiator for the Trail of Broken Treaties, whose supporters took over the BIA, complains that Loesch "exercises almost complete control of the BIA."</p>

<p>Loesch is accused of passing over BIA Commissioner Louis R. Bruce, a Mohawk Indian, and running the bureau of his Interior Department office across the street, or through Bruce's assistant, John Crow.</p>

<p>Crow's resignation also was called for by occupiers of the building.  Crow is a career Interior employee who was sent to BIA "because Loesch wouldn't demean himself by going over there, but didn't want Bruce (who also is a Presidential apointee) to run it," Adams said.</p>

<p>Adams accused Loesch of believing that "he knows what's best for Indians."  He said, "Loesch gets in the way of appropriate legal decisions regarding fishing and water rights by insisting that the (existing) federal position is protective of Indian interests, despite what Indians may say."</p>

<p>Judges are "more likely to listen to the assistant secretary than they are to an Indian," Adams said.</p>

<p>Peter MacDonald, chairman of the Navajo nation, criticizes Loesch for "coming to a conclusion too quickly."  As head of the nation's biggest Indian tribe, MacDonald has had many official dealings with the assistant secretary.</p>

<p>It's not that he's insensitive," MacDonald said, "but rather that he acts without a full view of the consequences."</p>

<p>MacDonald suggests that Loesch's snap judgments are better suited to land management responsibilities than to the BIA.  "There is a difference between dealing with land problems and human problems," MacDonald said.</p>

<p>He, too, believes Loesch should be fired, along with assistant BIA Commissioner Crow, who is an Indian.  Crow "appears to be used by those who oppose change," MacDonald said.</p>

<p>Crow has "been there so long that he has become a symbol of the old establishment.  Seeing his face for so long is a reminder that nothing has changed," he Navajo chairman said.</p>

<p>Loesch's attitude may be illustrated by his own examples of major accomplishments of his regime.</p>

<p>He cited the Central Arizona Project, a $1.2 billion land reclamation plan, as something which will "benefit 11 tribes, five in Arizona who favor it and six others who live along the Colorado River banks which fear it--unadvisably so."</p>

<p>The Pyramid Lake legal action also is viewed by Loesch as a plus for Interior, even though the department's actions were sharply criticized earlier this month by U.S. District Court Judge Gerhard A. Gesell.</p>

<p>Gesell found that Interior had permitted private developers to divert water from the Truckee River, which feeds the lake, a primary source of food and recreation for the Paiute Tribe near Reno.</p>

<p>The court action "dealt only with the tip of the iceberg," according to Loesch.</p>

<p>"The real question will be decided by the Supreme Court" in an action brought by the Justice Department in behalf of Interior, Loesch said.</p>

<p>Gesell's decision affected operating critera, which change annually, according to Loesch.  The assistant secretary, who believes he is an expert in water law, said he testified that "you can't justify requiring a particular amount of water in the lake because I'll guarantee you that if the water doesn't come down the river, it sure can't fill the lake.  But the judge just didn't buy my act."</p>

<p>Interior Secretary Rogers C. B. Morton also testified, "But Morton doesn't know any more about water than Judge Gesell does," Loesch said.</p>

<p>The Supreme Court action challenges a 1906 decision that went against Indian claims to water rights.  "If the Indians win that one, it will revolutionize water rights throughout the West," Loesch said.</p>

<p>He said he "conned" Morton into supporting the action.</p>

<p>Loesch admits to being "under fire" a lot of the time and "while I don't feel I'm to blame, you can get some other opinions on that."</p>

<p>"I've been criticized by urban-type Indians who are not part of my responsibility through BIA, but I believe the reservation Indians consider me a sympathetic and hard-working secretary.</p>

<p>"But Indians are just like the rest of us.  There's no community that agrees 100 per cent on anything and no tribe is unanimous either.</p>

<p>"I've learned there is no Indian problem, there are a jillion Indian problems.  Anyone who thinks otherwise is being utterly simplistic.</p>

<p>Loesch said he often feels like "you're wading through molasses, but when you look back, you can see accomplishments."</p>

<p>He sees the government's primary obligation to the reservation community as its "trust responsibility and how the government carries it out.  We need to see they get a fair shake on development, and this, of course, has not happened."</p>

<p>The greatest need is for a communications network--roads--"without which they can't do anything in education, medicine, business."</p>

<p>Roads on reservations are "disgraceful," Loesch said, although he believes Interior's five-year program, despite budget cuts ordered by the President, will make a dent in the backlog of $800 million worth of projects and survive with $75 million for roads.</p>

<p>"The Secretary made a helluva charge on that," he said</p>

<p>Loesch remains "gung ho" about the Indian Business Development program, although its initial request for $25 million got chopped to $4.4 million before it was appropriated in the spring of 1971.</p>

<p>The money provides grants, not loans, to Indian entrepreneurs to "get over that last little hump which can get them into business."</p>

<p>The program has "put 1,123 guys into business valued at $12 million on reservations," Loesch said.  The failure rate has been "fantastically" low.</p>

<p>"Sure we laid a couple of eggs--one guy took $14,000 and headed south--but a skilled roofer in Kansas used $4,000 to buy his boss' equipment, and now he employs four other Indians and is greatly successful."</p>

<p>The turnover of money within the community is needed for economic development, Loesch said.</p>

<p>In his hometown of Montrose, Colo., for instance, "a car dealer comes to my law office with a problem, I buy a car from him and he spends the money at the men's clothing store.  The money turns over three-four times before leaving town.</p>

<p>"In the Indian community, the money turns over one time.  An Indian needs to buy a pickup truck so he must drive outside the reservation to buy it, and zip, the money's gone.</p>

<p>"It will be a bottomless pit until there are Indian barbers, lawyers, carpendters," Loesch said.</p>

<p>"Of course, a lot of Indians don't want to get into business to go the white man's way," he added.  "But more are learning they can keep their Indianness and still get into business.</p>

<p>"We must ameliorate the economic problems which are endemic on reservations," Loesch said.</p>

<p>"I've been accused by radicals of being insensitive because I don't go around beating my chest and saying, 'Lo, the poor Indian.'</p>

<p>"Well, I don't buy the AIM act--I disagree with their methods--but I agree the government has been lax.  Through the '50s, and in the Johnson administration, there was no doubt the Indians were getting run over.</p>

<p>"But this administration is the best there ever was (for Indians)," Loesch said.</p>

<p>Before coming to Interior, Loesch had spent his entire life in Montrose, population 5,000, except for four years in the Air Corps in World War II, and schooling at Colorado College and Denver and Yale law schools.</p>

<p>He was born in Chicago, but "that was only because my mother didn't trust the doctors in Montrose.  So she went back to Chicago for the delivery.  We were there about three weeks."</p>

<p>Loesch (pronounced Lesh), 56, had "never been in politics, although I have been a Republican since the end of the war.  The highest party position I ever held was finance chairman of the Montrose County GOP, and in a county with 18,000 residents, you can imagine what a big deal that was."</p>

<p>His knowledge of the Interior Department was primarily as an adversary, "taking 'em to court," in behalf of clients who were opposed to various agencies, Park Service, Reclamation, the Bureau of Land management in a county which is 70 per cent public land.</p>

<p>His political connection has been Sen. Gordon L. Allott, "who had gone to school with my wife."  (Allott, however, was defeated this month in a bid for a fourth term.  Loesch believes Allott's defeat would "erode" his support in a fight, but he doesn't anticipate a fight.)</p>

<p>A mutual friend, a Denver laywer, acting as a go-between, called Loesch to ask if he might be interested in coming to Washington.</p>

<p>"I told him yes, thinking it was a (legal) case, and asked how long I would be there.  He said 'permanently, they want you to be assistant secretary of the Interior.'</p>

<p>"This guy has a reputation as a practical joker, so I said, 'If they don't want me for secretary, I'm not interested."</p>

<p>At lunch, Loesch told his wife, Louise, about the call.  She convinced him to call Jack Ware, Sen. Allott's administrative aide.</p>

<p>Ware confirmed that the offer was solid, and "two weeks later I was in Washington."</p>

<p>Left behind was a law practice built up over 29 years, and three law partners who were "calling every day for two months asking where I had put someting."</p>

<p>Because presidential appointees must sever all business connections, "I sold out at a fire sale price" to the partners.  But the move "was not a financial sacrifice."</p>

<p>Loesch said he had been making $25,000 to $30,000 a year in Montrose and that he and his wife considered the Level 4 position, paying $38,000 a year "to be a little raised," which he soon learned was "wrong as hell."</p>

<p>He also was wrong about something else:  "I had the usual citizen's view that all these bureaucrats were just sitting around."  But in his first year on the job "I never got here later than 7:30 in the morning and never left before 7:30 at night, and didn't take a vacation."</p>

<p>As his knowledge of the job increased, his hours decreased, but Loesch still is at his desk most nights at 6, and comes in on Saturdays to go over the mail.</p>

<p>He and Mrs. Loesch have a rental apartment in the Columbia Towers, which is "next to that other place" (the Watergate).  Their only child, Jeffery, is a graduate student at the University of Minnesota.</p>

<p>Loesch denigrates his own appointment with the observation that "when Nixon came in, this administration was stupid--better make that unskilled--in filling sub-cabinet jobs."</p>

<p>He learned that "three of four others had been shot down" for the post for conflicts of interest or other reasons and that although "Allott had spent all his chips in other places," when the Colorado Republican got another chance "he thought of me.  He admired my brains and knew that I knew something about public land."</p>

<p>If his criticism of government chieftains costs Loesch his job, he's prepared to go back to the private practice of law.</p>

<p>He's likely to go West again, where "you're two minutes from home, office, golf course, trout stream and ski slope."  It probably won't be in his hometown, however, because "in a small town, sooner or later a lawyer has sued everybody in town.</p>

<p>"Besides that, this job has opened other doors.  I'll probably find something more remunerative."</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="pA11"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi>  <hi rend="italic">  Washington Post</hi>, December 02, 1972, p. A11.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">BIA Fight: 'One Has to Go'</head>

<p>A White House spokesman last night reacted to namecalling by a top official of the Bureau of Indian Affairs by saying "we are sick and tired of the polarization" there and promised that "measures will be taken to get rid of it."</p>

<p>The spokesman said that Deputy Commissioner John O. Crow's denouncement of his boss, BIA Commissioner Louis R. Bruce Jr., "spreads right out in front of you the kind of shape that place is in."</p>

<p>Crow, reacting to planned reduction in staff and other changes by Bruce, said "one of us has to go.  I've tried to work with him and tried to help, but I've reached the end of my rope."</p>

<p>Bruce would not engage in an attack on Crow, but rather said he was "extremely proud of the new directions and new programs" developed in the bureau under his leadership.</p>

<p>Bruce said that "because of pending congressional hearings, I have no statement relating to remarks made regarding my doncut during the recent takeover . . . Judgements relating to this are obviously premature in light of upcoming hearings and/or investigations."</p>

<p>On Monday, the House Indian Affairs Subcommittee, chaired by Rep. James A. Haley (D-Fla.) will begin three days of hearings on the government's handling of a protest last month that led to a six-day occupation of the BIA building by Indian demonstrators.  Bruce is to be one of the witnesses on Monday.</p>

<p>A second inquiry has been set for early next year by Sen. Edward M. Kennedy (D-Mass.).  Of Crow's criticism of Bruce, the White House spokesman said, "I've rarely seen such an example of polarization" within a government agency.</p>

<p>He said corrective measures will be taken "soon," meaning some time this month.  The spokesman would not say whether the shakeup would involve Crow, or Bruce, or both, but said "they can't serve the people they are meant to serve" and fight among themselves.</p>

<p>Bruce said he has had "great support from Interior Secretary (Rogers C. B.) Morton, from key members of Congress and the White House.</p>

<p>"It isn't, nor will it be, easy to change the oldest bureaucracy in the federal government," Bruce said.  He said that while he had "a lot of help to accomplish these changes from many career BIA employees, a few apparently feel extremely uncomfrotable as a result of these changes.</p>

<p>"I regret this, for their struggle against inevitable change only harms the Indian people . . . The federal government should acknowledge Indian sovereignty, expand and improve the federal trust services and help Indian tribes develop their own local governments," so that they can truly begin to call the shots.</p>

<p>Crow, a 38-year employee of the Department of the Interior, said he received no criticism from any higher ranking employee because of his statement.</p>

<p>Assistant Secretary of the Interior Harrison Loesch, who has over-all responsibility for the BIA, "kind of laughed" when he heard about the statement, Crow said.</p>

<p>"I kind of took a page out of his (Loesch's) book," said Crow in reference to the outspoken assistant secretary.</p>

<p>Loesch and Crow were two of the federal officials singled out for criticism by leaders of the Trail of Broken Treaties, who occupied the BIA building.</p>

<p>Crow said his break with Bruce followed Bruce's handling of the demonstration.  "I don't like the support he gave to the unruly mob," Crow said.  "He couldn't administer anything.  He is just compounding the situation."</p>

<p>The deputy commissioner acknowledged that "it sure is unusual for an appointive official to publicly criticize his superior, but "times have changed since I was brought up in this business."</p>

<p>He said that because he is eligible for retirement, "I'm working for nothing, just about, because I like what I'm doing."</p>

<p>Crow said there is "a good possibility" that both he and Bruce will be fired as a result of the split.</p>

<p>Bruce, who is a Mohawk, and Crow, who is part Cherokee, are appointed by different officials.  The commissioner is a presidential appointee and his deputy an appointee of the Secretary of the Interior.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>



<text>
<body>

<pb n="pC1"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi>  <hi rend="italic">  Washington Post</hi>, December 04, 1972, p. C1.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Employees of BIA To Resume Work</head>

<p>The new acting director of the Bureau of Indian Affairs said yesterday that he expects all BIA employees to be back at their desks Wednesday, ending more than a month of paid leave for many of the bureau's 450 employees.</p>

<p>Richard S. Bodman, named by Interior Secretary Rogers C. B. Morton to reorganize the strife-torn bureau, said that he met yesterday with about a dozen BIA officials and "established a chain of command."</p>

<p>The reorganization came on the eve of a House investigation into the government's handling of nearly 1,000 demonstrators who occupied the BIA building for six days last month.</p>

<p>Bodman said department heads ranking just below the bureau's two top administrators "gave me an expression of confidence."  Bodman, who is assistant secretary of Interier for management and budget, was picked Saturday to "put Indian operations back to work" after the three federal officials primarily responsible for Indian affairs were relieved of their duties by Morton.</p>

<p>Two of those officials, Harrison Loesch, assistant secretary of Interior for land management and Indian affairs, and Louis R. Bruce Jr., BIA commissioner, are scheduled to testify today before the House Subcommittee on Indian Affairs.  The official relieved was John O. Crow, deputy commissioner of the BIA.</p>

<p>Rep. James Haley (D-Fla.) has set aside three days to hear testimony about the protest and resulting damage.  Haley's inquiry will deal only with the government's role in handling the Trail of Broken Treaties caravan.</p>

<p>Participants said they came here from across the country to meet peacefully with federal officials on 20 specific grievances, but when negotiations over housing broke down, caravan members refused to leave the BIA building.</p>

<p>Before they finally left it on Nov. 8, every office in the four-story building at 19th Street and Constitution Avenue NW was vandalized.  Damage originally was calculated at more than $2 million.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="pA5"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Washington Post</hi>, February 01, 1973, p. A5.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">Activists' House Raided Again; BIA Documents Sought</head>

<p>The three-story brick row house at 1747 Lanier Pl. NW has been occupied by a variety of newsworthy persons in the last few years: Lesie Bacon, once a suspect in the 1971 bombing of the Capitol, and a series of May Day, Cantonsville 9 and other antiwar activists and rebel American Indians.</p>

<p>Yesterday, the FBI moved in.</p>

<p>From shortly before noon until 5, four agents, in shifts of two, took turns sitting at the dining room table, listening to tape recorded Indian music and chatting with the regular tenants, two Indian women and their three young children.</p>

<p>They said they were waiting for a search warrant needed to search the rambling house for documents stolen from the Bureau of Indian Affairs building last November.</p>

<p>A Paiute-Shoshone Indian woman, Anita Collins, 28, had been led away from the house in handcuffs shortly before noon.</p>

<p>Mrs. Collins, Henry L. (Hank) Adams, 29, of 1464 Rhode Island Ave. NW, chief negotiator for the Trail of Broken Treaties, and Les Whitten, a reporter for newspaper columnist Jack Anderson, were charged with receiving stolen government property.</p>

<p>There were no warrants for the other residents: LaNada Boyer, 26, a Bannock-Shoshone from Idaho who is a student at Antioch Law School; her sons, Deynon, 5, and Gerad, 4 months; her niece Leana Angel, 19, and Mrs. Angel's daughter, Anee, 22 months.</p>

<p>So the agents sat and drank instant coffee, getting up only to follow the women through the house, or to trade places with agents sitting outside in a car.</p>

<p>The agents were impassive in the presence of tape recorded music which blared and sage and cedar "medicine," which burned, and children who fussed and squealed.</p>

<p>Mrs. Boyer said the agents came to the house in the company of a man named Johnny, who had posed as an Indian, gaining their confidence, only to reveal himself yesterday as an undercover agent.</p>

<p>"You're a traitor, Johnny," Mrs. Boyer said she told him when he knocked at the door with a warrant for Mrs. Collins' arrest.</p>

<p>"I'm not an Indian," she said he responded.  "I'm an officer," he said, flashing his credentials.</p>

<p>"You're an American, aren't you?" the woman replied.</p>

<p>Mrs. Boyer said Johnny had helped Mrs. Collins move her belongings to the house on Monday, and had offered his red station wagon for their use in picking up some "documents" at the bus depot on Tuesday.</p>

<p>Documents reportedly stolen during the Indian takeover of the BIA building, were returned to Adams, who in turn planned to return them to the BIA yesterday, Mrs. Boyer said.  She said Adams had an appointment with a BIA official.</p>

<p>As the wait became prolonged, Mrs. Boyer chided the agents about their lack of knowledge of Indian history.</p>

<p>She said she and her son, Deynon Means, were among the first 14 Indians who occupied Alcatraz Island in San Francisco Bay, beginning Nov. 20, 1969.</p>

<p>They stayed on the rock one year.  Mrs. Boyer hitched boat rides to the mainland often enough to continue her studies at the University of California at Berkeley.  At that time, she was married to Ted Means, a leader of the occupation and brother of Russell Means, an organizer of the American Indian Movement (AIM) one of the sponsors of last November's caravan to Washington.</p>

<p>Mrs. Boyer said she graduated from Berkeley in December, 1972, with a degree in Indian law and politics.  Her son became known as "the Alcatraz kid," she said.</p>

<p>At 4:15 p.m., Sen. James Abourezk (D-S.D.) called for information.  Mrs. Boyer told him the agents were "pacing around, following us to the bathroom and things like that."</p>

<p>Fellow students from Antioch Law School called and advised the women that they should walk out, and demand that the agents leave, too.</p>

<p>So at 4:55 p.m., four agents, two women and three children--one of them wrapped snugly in an Indian cradle board--vacated 1747 Lanier Pl. NW.  The agents remained outside explaining that the house was still "secured."</p>

<p>The landlady, Mrs. Dean Thompson, who lives in the other half of the building, at 1749, had come about 4 p.m.  Her reaction was: "I hope they (FBI) don't break down the door again, as they did when they came after Leslie Bacon."</p>

<p>Mrs. Thompson said Mrs. Boyer had been a good tenant, and is up-to-date on the rent.</p>

<p>Mrs. Boyer explained that she is able to pay the rent because of a law school scholarship she was awarded for being the only member of her tribe ever to graduate from college.</p>

<p>The scholarship is provided by the Bureau of Indian Affairs, she said.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>


<text>
<body>

<pb n="pA1"/>

<div1 type="summary">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Summary:</hi>  ........</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="source">
	<p><hi rend="underline">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">  Washington Post</hi>, February 01, 1973, p. A1.</p>
</div1>

<milestone unit="smallbar"/>

<div1 type="body">

<head type="main">FBI Arrests Reporter in Stolen Data</head>

<p>FBI agents arrested Leslie H. Whitten, investigative reporter for columnist Jack Anderson, on a Washington street yesterday and charged him, along with two other persons, with illegally receiving documents stolen from the Bureau of Indian Affairs last November.</p>

<p>Whitten, 44, denied any illegal involvement and said he was arrested while "covering the story" of the documents' return to the government.</p>

<p>Charged with Whitten in a one-page criminal complaint were Henry L. (Hank) Adams, 29, of 1464 Rhode Island Ave. NW, and Anita Collins, 28, of 1747 Lanier Pl. NW.</p>

<p>The charge carries a maximum penalty of a $10,000 fine and a year in jail.</p>

<p>Adams, an Assiniboine Sioux from Frank's Landing, Wash., was chief negotiator for the Trail of Broken Treaties, a coalition of Indian groups that organized a caravan to Washington that resulted in the takeover of the BIA building Nov. 2 through Nov. 8.</p>

<p>Mrs. Collins, a Paiute Shoshone, previously lived in Alexandria.  She also was a planner of the caravan.</p>

<p>All three were arrested at 10:15 a.m., and were held in a lockup at the U.S. Courthouse for five hours.  They were released on their own recognizance after brief appearances before U.S. magistrate Jean Dwyer.</p>

<p>A preliminary hearing was scheduled for Feb. 15 to determine whether there is probable cause to hold them for grand jury action.</p>

<p>Last week two Indians were arrested in Kansas City, Mo., on similar charges of possession of material stolen from the BIA.  Several other indictments were returned earlier in Oklahoma, but they have since been dismissed.</p>

<p>The BIA building, at 19th Street and Constitution Ave. NW, was sacked during the occupation, and much of its contents was destroyed or stolen.</p>

<p>Anderson, whose column has carried extensive quotations from stolen BIA documents, charged the federal government with "harassment" of a newsman who had been reponsible for stories that were "embarrassing" to federal officials.</p>

<p>Whitten emerged smiling from his confinement and told reporters, "I was just out covering the story and I got arrested by the FBI.  I hope it doesn't happen to anyone else."</p>

<p>Anderson acknowledged that at the time of the arrests, Whitten was helping Adams in the physical transportation of three cartons of BIA documents.  That was because Adams, who had made arrangements to return the material to the BIA, lacked his own transportation, Anderson said.</p>

<p>FBI agents made the arrests in front of the apartment house where Adams lives and maintains a headquarters for his campaign of protest against alleged official violantions of the rights of American Indians.</p>

<p>After the arrest, a reporter visited Adams' fifth-floor apartment.  He talked to two FBI agents there who said they were waiting for Michael Hunt, who works as a bodyguard for Adams.  The apartment was in disarray.</p>

<p>At 1747 Lanier Pl. NW, FBI agents waited inside the house throughout the afternoon for a search warrant that was not delivered.</p>

<p>An FBI spokesman said that after the street arrest, agents then went to Adams' apartment and arrested Daniel Pigeon, 22, of Wittenberg, Wis., and Alison Grace Cerri, 20, of 9316 Piney Branch Parkway, Silver Spring.  Pigeon and Miss Cerri also were held throughout the day but were released at 6 p.m. when the U.S. Attorney's office announced that no charges would be placed against them.</p>

<p>According to the complaint, an unidentified undercover District policeman informed the FBI that he had learned on Tuesday that Whitten would pick up the documents at the Rhode Island Avenue address.</p>

<p>Whitten's account was significantly different.  He said the arrangement to accompany Adams and to observe the return of the documents was made over the telephone at 8:45 a.m. yesterday.</p>

<p>The complaint charged Whitten, Adams, and Mrs. Collins with receiving, concealing and retaining the three cartons with intent to convert them to their own use, knowing that they were stolen, a violation of Section 641 of the federal criminal code.</p>

<p>According to Whitten, he and Adams marked the cartons with the name of Dennis Hyten, the special FBI agent they knew was working on the investigation of the November lootings of the BIA offices.</p>

<p>The idea was to drop off the cartons at the BIA, with the expectation that they would be forwarded to agent Hyten, Whitten said.  Anderson told newsmen that during a fingerprinting and photographing session at the FBI Washington field office, Whitten made a special request that agents take pictures of the cartons marked with Hyten's name, apparently to corroborate Whitten's contention that the documents were being restored to government control.</p>

<p>Anderson said no such photographs were taken in Whitten's presence.  An FBI spokesman refused to comment on any events occuring during the identification procedures.</p>

<p>Whitten said he asked to go to FBI headquarters and the courthouse without the assistance of agents, but he was handcuffed and escorted along with Adams and Mrs. Collins.</p>

<p>Whitten, a former reporter for The Washington Post and the Washington bureau of the Hearst newspapers, has been an associate of Jack Anderson since 1969.</p>

<p>Anderson told reporters that Whitten "is incapable of telling a falsehood.  He was at all times acting as a newsman.  He had nothing to do with the theft of the documents, and he was simply trying to get another exclusive story about the return of the documents and the government's reaction."</p>

<p>Anderson said that neither he nor Whitten had ever been in possession of original BIA papers.  He said his office dealt only with Xerox copies.</p>

<p>The unusual procedure, Anderson said, was for Whitten to sift through hundreds of pages of BIA papers and designate the pages which his Indian sources would duplicate and turn over.</p>

<p>The papers document years of BIA abuse of Indian rights, Anderson said.  He added that he intends to run further columns based on information from the documents.</p>

<p>The columnist said he was not condoming theft but neither was he approving of federal treatment of American Indians.</p>

<p>The Reporters Committee for Freedom of the Press, which has taken part in several legal cases involving reporters, issued a statement charging that the arrest of Whitten "is based on the outrageous proposition that information about government activities is property, like an auto, which can be owned by the government . . .</p>

<p>"Government information belongs to the public.  It is not owned by the Defense Department or the President or the Bureau of Indian Affairs."</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>